<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/EHRI/ehri-online-editions/main/ODD/out/ODD_EHRI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="EHRI-DR-19420327-IT_EN">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title xml:lang="en">Carlo Alberto de Vera d'Aragona on Measures Against the Jews in Slovakia in 1942</title>
				<title xml:lang="de">Carlo Alberto de Vera d'Aragona über Maßnahmen gegen die Juden in der Slowakei im Jahr 1942</title>
				<principal><affiliation><orgName>European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</orgName></affiliation></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Edited by</resp>
					<orgName>EHRI Edition of Diplomatic Reports</orgName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>
					<ref target="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</ref>
				</authority>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title>Diplomatic Reports</title>
			</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<institution><orgName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/institutions/it-002863">Archivio Storico Diplomatico del Ministero degli Affari Esteri</orgName><address>
								<street>Piazzale della Farnesina, 1</street>
								<postCode>00196</postCode>
								<settlement>Roma</settlement>
								<country ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/countries/it">Italy</country>
							</address></institution>
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
				<bibl>Archivio Storico Diplomatico del Ministero degli Affari Esteri, AG Uff, fasc. Slovakia.<textLang mainLang="it"> Original in Italian.</textLang></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p xml:lang="fr">L'encodage de ce document s'est fait dans le cadre du travail sur les éditions en ligne EHRI</p>
				<p xml:lang="en">The encoding of this document is part of the work on the EHRI Online Editions</p>
				<p xml:lang="de">Die Kodierung dieses Dokuments ist Teil der Arbeit an den EHRI Online Editions</p>
			</projectDesc>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation><origDate when="1942-03-27">27.3.1942</origDate>
				<origPlace ref="http://www.geonames.org/727011/sofia.html">Sofia</origPlace>
				<persName ref="#ehri_dr_deVeradaragona_carlo_alberto">de Vera d’Aragona, Carlo Alberto</persName>
			</creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="it"/>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2024-05-27" who="#floriane.chiffoleau">Upgrading TEI encoding</change>
			<change when-iso="2021" who="#ehri">Encoding of the file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="transcription">
				<div type="original">
					<p>The original transcription is not available.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="translation">
					<p>Report of the 1st Secretary of the Legation, <persName ref="#ehri_dr_deVeradaragona_carlo_alberto">Carlo Alberto de Vera d’Aragona</persName> to the Italian Ministry of Foreign Affairs.</p>
					<p>Incoming telegram no. 2356 R.</p>
					<p>By courier</p>
					<p>Decoded by: SE – Cleartext</p>
					<p>R. Legation <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/3060972/bratislava.html">Bratislava</placeName> 27.3.42.XX</p>
					<p>Bratislava, 6.4.42.XX</p>
					<p>Copy modified in assigning</p>
					<p>Assigned to A.G.</p>
					<p>A.E.M.</p>
					<p>Re: <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/terezin-terms-keyword-jmp-542" type="subject">Measures against the Jews</term></p>
					<p>014 - The new measures against the <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-864" type="subject">Jews</term> that had been announced have all of a sudden seen a drastic implementation. <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-872" type="subject">Ten thousand Jews</term> in towns and in villages had received personal summonses in order to be assembled in <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-496" type="subject">concentration camps</term>.</p>
					<p>Due to the ease with which one may convert to the <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-771" type="subject">evangelical Church</term> and because many of those summoned were aware that public opinion was mostly opposed to the <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-342" type="subject">anti-Semitic campaign</term>, and also because <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-852" type="subject">rumour</term> had it that the President of the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/3057568/slovak-republic.html">Republic</placeName>, Monsignor <persName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_pers-000789">Tiso</persName>, was indirectly opposed to such methods of persecution, many Jews did not comply with the
							<term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-339" type="subject">orders</term> given by <persName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_pers-000261">Minister Mach</persName> . So in the night from 23rd to 24th March patrols formed by <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-1119" type="subject">police and Guardsmen</term> who had been joined by <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-1216" type="subject">SS men</term> arrived from over the nearby border, entered
						Jewish homes, seized three thousand women aged 18 to 35 years, and carried them swiftly on a lorry to the munitions factory in Bratislava and to the internment areas of <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/3058531/nitra.html">Nitra</placeName>, <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/3056508/zilina.html">Žilina</placeName>, <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/723819/presov.html">Prešov</placeName>, etc.</p>
					<p>The Authorities closest to the President are denying or trying to downplay the extent of the events that have clearly shaken the public opinion here, although everyone knows that the originator of this undertaking is <persName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_pers-000261">Minister Mach</persName>, Commander of the <orgName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_cb-397">Hlinka Guard</orgName>, who is being instigated by elements from beyond the border and by
						others who oppose the President, and who accuses the <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-864" type="subject">Jews</term> themselves of being responsible for everything and deserving of the worst punishments.</p>
					<p>It is well-known that the Minister of Interior, who is entirely subservient to the orders from beyond the Danube, intends to gradually carry out the concentration and mass deportation of all the <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-864" type="subject">Israelites</term> of <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/3057568/slovak-republic.html">Slovakia</placeName>, that is approximately 70 thousand souls, the older ones to the <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-1191">General Governorate of
							Poland</term> (<placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/765876/lublin.html">Lublin</placeName> area) and the younger to Ukrainian locations, to be employed in farm labour and in the Organisation Todt. However, since at least for the time being they are mostly women still
						in the bloom of youth and of good social standing, no doubt their employ will be of an entirely different character and purpose, in the train of the German units operating in southern Russia.</p>
					<p>The announcement of harsher anti-Semitic measures had already prompted the Holy See to deliver a note to the Minister of Slovakia, Mister Sidor; the persecutions that have since taken place have then given rise to repeated démarches on the part of the Apostolic Delegate,
						Monsignor Burzio, with Prime Minister <persName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_pers-000413">Tuka</persName>. As things now stand, the events described above have caused a rift not yet made public but dangerous between Prime Minister <persName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_pers-000413">Tuka</persName> and <persName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_pers-000261">Minister Mach</persName> on the one side and President <persName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_pers-000789">Tiso</persName> on the other. The consequences are easy to predict if the anti-Semitic persecution should continue in the manner reported above and the President of the Republic, being a cleric and a parish
						priest with the care of souls, should sooner or later be faced with a serious crisis of conscience.</p>
					<p><persName ref="#ehri_dr_deVeradaragona_carlo_alberto">De Vera</persName></p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>