<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://gitlab.inria.fr/dh-projects/workflow-ehri/-/raw/main/ODD/out/ODD-EHRI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="EHRI-DR-19420615-DK_EN" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title xml:lang="en">Otto Carl Mohr on "The Position of the Jews" in Ostland in 1942</title>
				<principal><affiliation><orgName>European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</orgName></affiliation></principal>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>
					<ref target="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</ref>
				</authority>
				<availability>
					<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title ref="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">EHRI Edition of Diplomatic Reports</title>
			</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/countries/dk">Denmark </country>
						<repository ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/institutions/dk-002313"> Rigsarkivet Danish National Archives </repository>
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
				<bibl>Rigsarkivet, 140.J.11a, Gruppeordnede sager. <textLang mainLang="en">Original in Danish.</textLang></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation>
				<date when="1942-06-15">15.06.1942</date>
				<placeName ref="#berlin">Berlin</placeName>
				<persName ref="#ehri_dr_mohr_otto_carl">Mohr, Otto Carl</persName>
				<idno>EHRI-DR-19420615-DK</idno>
			</creation>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="transcription">
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420615_01" n="1"/>
				<p>Just like the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/maps/wikipedia_52.5167_13.4">German Empire</placeName>, a number of special
						<term ref="#t1033" type="subject">provisions</term> apply to <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> in <term
						ref="#t1181" type="subject">Ostland</term>. These Regulations are only to a very limited extent drawn up by the <term
						ref="#t1112" type="subject">administrative Authorities. </term> Thus, only a single related regulation is seen to have been
					issued by the <orgName ref="#g485">Minister of State for the Occupied Eastern Territories</orgName>, see below under B.VIII, and
					the Office of the Commissioner of the Interior essentially confines himself to an Order of <date when="1941-10-13">13
						October</date> of the previous year, regarding the Treatment of <term ref="#t888" type="subject">Jewish Wealth</term> in the
					State Commission of <term ref="#t1181" type="subject">Ostland</term>. The Area Commissioners or the Self-<term ref="#t948"
						type="subject">Government</term> administrative Authorities have drafted the vast majority of provisions, and many of these
					Provisions are hardly published. As a result, the contents of the <term ref="#t542" type="subject">regulations</term> in question
					are more difficult to access for the legation, and there may also be some minor differences in the rules at the various locations.
					In the following, the legation will refer to some of the <term ref="#t337" type="subject">special provisions</term> applicable to
					the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> of <term ref="#t1181" type="subject">Ostland</term>. Because of the foregoing, it
					is not certain that all the rules made <pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420615_02" n="2"/> under B. IV to VII apply throughout <term
						ref="#t1181" type="subject">Ostland</term>. However, the envoy has intended to refrain from conducting an examination of the
					extent to which they are applicable everywhere, as their applicability in most places is undoubted, and it is probably more the
					general principles which have been adopted by the <term ref="#t1032" type="subject">authorities</term>. The following draws upon
					some of the <term ref="#t337" type="subject">Special Provisions</term> of Interest.</p>
				<p>A. So far there is no <term ref="#t365" type="subject">provision</term> for what is meant by the term '<term ref="#t864"
						type="subject">Jew</term>'.</p>
				<p>However, one would assume that the rules of this term in <term ref="#t1181" type="subject">Ostland</term>, are similar to the <term
						ref="#t952" type="subject">ones</term> used in <term ref="#t1159?dlid=deu" type="subject">Germany</term>. […]</p>
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420615_03" n="3"/>
				<p>B.I. The <persName ref="#p000254">Commissioner of State</persName> issued on <date when="1941-10-13">13 October</date> of the
					previous year a decree on Treatment of <term ref="#t887" type="subject">Jewish assets</term> in the <ref
						target="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/admindistricts-74">Reich Commissariat Ostland</ref>, stating that all the
						<term ref="#t888" type="subject">wealth</term> of the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jewich population</term> has been
					subject to <term ref="#t585" type="subject">seizure</term>, commissarial administration and <term ref="#t584" type="subject"
						>confiscation</term> in accordance with the provisions contained in the device. This includes <term ref="#t887" type="subject"
						>assets</term> of all kinds, such as real estate and movable property with all accessories and claims, rights and all kinds of
					interests.</p>
				<p><term ref="#t333" type="subject">The right of confiscation</term> is the responsibility of the Commissioner of State or the
					authority, which he announces. It may include individual persons or the <term ref="#t872" type="subject">Jews</term> as a whole,
					and it may be restricted to individual <term ref="#t887" type="subject">property</term>. Excluded from the seizure is the part of
					the household deemed necessary for the personal life and cash, <term ref="#t930" type="subject">bank</term> and savings deposits
					and securities at a total value of 100 Reichsmark. […]</p>
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420615_05" n="5"/>
				<p>Even before the Completion of the administrative <term ref="#t951" type="subject">order</term> of <date when="1941-10-13">13
						October</date> of the previous year, There were within the various areas of which <term ref="#t1181" type="subject"
						>Ostland</term> consists, local regulations, which had been drawn up, imposing a registration requirement for all <term
						ref="#t887" type="subject">Jewish property</term> and prohibiting the <term ref="#t872" type="subject">Jews</term> from
					disposing of their property.</p>
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420615_06" n="6"/>
				<p>II. In the cities, the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jewich population</term> lives in special <term ref="#t545" type="subject"
						>Jewish neighbourhoods</term>, separated from the rest of the city by high barricades. <term ref="#t546" type="subject">Within
						the Ghetto</term>, the <term ref="#t872" type="subject">Jews</term> are allowed to move freely, but they are prohibited from
					leaving the confined areas and could be sentenced to the death penalty if they do so and do not have special permission. The <term
						ref="#t872" type="subject">Jews</term> living in the <term ref="#t545" type="subject">ghettos</term> belong to their own
					administration, choosing a kind of <term ref="#t579" type="subject">Jewish Council</term>, which through its <term ref="#t554"
						type="subject">chairman</term> is obliged to receive the orders of the <term ref="#t477" type="subject">authorities</term>
					concerning the <term ref="#t872" type="subject">Jews</term>. The Chairman is responsible for the execution of such orders. All the
						<term ref="#t872" type="subject">Jews</term> shall always obey the authorities’ provisions, which he issues.</p>
				<p>III. All <term ref="#t872" type="subject">Jews</term> are committed to wear a yellow <term ref="#t338" type="subject">Star of
						David</term>, 8 to 10 cm in diameter on their chest - in for example <placeName ref="#republic-of-lithuania"
						>Lithuania</placeName> also on their back.</p>
				<p>IV. All <term ref="#t872" type="subject">Jews</term> that are able to <term ref="#t556" type="subject">work</term> must do so. They
					are employed through the Employment Office. For the work done by the <term ref="#t872" type="subject">Jews</term>, the employers
					must pay a <term ref="#t1050" type="subject">tariff wage</term>, but the labour profits are <term ref="#t1048" type="subject">not
						paid directly</term>, but they are paid to the authorities. These then pay what the <term ref="#t872" type="subject"
						>Jews</term> have earned for the work done to the Council mentioned under II, which in then settles with the individual.</p>
				<p>V. <term ref="#t872" type="subject">Jews</term> must not employ <term ref="#t373" type="subject">Aryan people</term> or give them
					shelter, a <term ref="#t1045" type="subject">provision</term> that has a special significance for Jews in the <term ref="#t944"
						type="subject">country area</term>.</p>
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420615_07" n="7"/>
				<p>VI. The <term ref="#t872" type="subject">Jews</term> are prohibited from using all <term ref="#t939" type="subject">public
						transport</term>. They are also <term ref="#t594" type="subject">prohibited</term> from staying in any public facility and
					park, visiting any <term ref="#t1071" type="subject">public venue</term>, restaurant, places of amusement, museums, theatres and
					bathing places. In <placeName ref="#republic-of-lithuania">Lithuania</placeName>, they are not allowed to walk on the sidewalk,
					but are forced to use the right-hand side of the street thus two Jews are not allowed to walk beside each other but must follow
					one another.</p>
				<p>The special permits required for bicycling in <term ref="#t1181" type="subject">Ostland</term> must not be issued to Jews.</p>
				<p>VII. For the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jewish population</term>, special <term ref="#t834" type="subject">food cards</term>
					have been issued for which, in general, only <term ref="#t569" type="subject">half</term> of the rations given to the rest of the
					native population are given. Generally, they have to make their purchases in certain designated stores. […]</p>
				<p>VIII. According to the Prime Minister's Decree of <date when="1941-12-19">19 December 1941</date> on the Establishment and
					Construction of a <term ref="#t1152" type="subject">German</term> Jurisdiction in the <term ref="#t1181" type="subject">Occupied
						Eastern Areas</term> (§ 5), Jews do not have remedies against a <term ref="#t1152" type="subject">German</term> court
					decision. Nor can they petition for a resumption of a case or require a <term ref="#t1213" type="subject">judge</term> to vacate
					his seat on grounds of disobedience.</p>
				<p>According to one of the <ref target="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/admindistricts-86">Commissioner-General of the
						Reval</ref> issued on <date when="1942-03-03">March 3, 1942</date>, the Order for the Provisional Execution of Justice through
					the country's own judicial authorities (§ 4), all <term ref="#t899" type="subject">Jews</term>, <term ref="#t864" type="subject"
						>Jewish</term>
					<q><term ref="#t374" type="subject">Mischlinge</term></q> or persons who are <term ref="#t582" type="subject">
						<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420615_08" n="8"/> married to Jews</term> or in a straight line, excluded from any undertaking in the
					national administration of justice.</p>
				<p><persName ref="#ehri_dr_mohr_otto_carl">Otto Carl Mohr</persName></p>
				<p/>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
