<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://gitlab.inria.fr/dh-projects/workflow-ehri/-/raw/main/ODD/out/ODD-EHRI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="EHRI-DR-19420910-DK_EN" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title xml:lang="en">Vincens Steensen-Leth debates potential aid for a Jewish woman in Germany married to a Dane in 1942</title>
				<principal><affiliation><orgName>European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</orgName></affiliation></principal>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>
					<ref target="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</ref>
				</authority>
				<availability>
					<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title ref="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">EHRI Edition of Diplomatic Reports</title>
			</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/countries/dk">Denmark </country>
						<repository ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/institutions/dk-002313"> Rigsarkivet Danish National Archives </repository>
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
				<bibl>Rigsarkivet, 17.E. Tys. 12/100, Gruppeordnede sager. <textLang mainLang="en">Original in Danish.</textLang></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation>
				<date when="1942-09-10">10.09.1942</date>
				<placeName ref="#berlin">Berlin</placeName>
				<persName ref="#ehri_dr_steensen-leth_vincens">Steensen-Leth, Vincens</persName>
				<idno>EHRI-DR-19420910-DK</idno>
			</creation>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="transcription">
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420910_01.jpg" n="1"/>
				<p>Dear<persName ref="#ehri_dr_hansen_jakob_hans">Hans Jakob Hansen</persName>,</p>
				<p>Thank you for your kind letter of l.ds. P.J.I.Jr.No. 17.E. Tys.12 / 100, concerning Mrs. Martha Hagen. I understand, that in
						<placeName ref="#kingdom-of-denmark">Danish</placeName> circles, where the <placeName ref="#federal-republic-of-germany"
						>German</placeName>
					<term ref="#t815" type="subject">attitude</term> to the <term ref="#t351" type="subject">Jewish question</term> has not yet
					penetrated, we can be somewhat disappointed with the weak results in these cases and tend to think that we are too reluctant on
					the part of the envoy and would, therefore, like to try, as far as possible in a letter, to redress our difficulties.</p>
				<p>The official <term ref="#t594" type="subject">German attitude</term> towards the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term>
					gradually becomes more and more severe as the <term ref="#t1080" type="subject">war</term> progresses. The <term ref="#t864"
						type="subject">Jews</term> are seen as the enemies of the People and they want to get rid of them, at best through isolation
					in <term ref="#t545" type="subject">ghettos</term> in the designated areas. This attitude applies to the <term ref="#t864"
						type="subject">Jews</term> as a <term ref="#t328" type="subject">race</term> without regard to <term ref="#t1147"
						type="subject">citizenship</term>, and the goal is the introduction of a <term ref="#t365" type="subject">Jewish law</term>
					similar to the German throughout <placeName ref="#europe">Europe</placeName>, that is, also in <placeName
						ref="#kingdom-of-denmark">Denmark</placeName>.</p>
				<p>So far, the <term ref="#t1149" type="subject">foreign Jews</term> in Germany are spared some of the most rigorous <term ref="#t951"
						type="subject">provisions</term>, but it is clear that even non-German <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term>, in due
					course, <pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420910_02.jpg" n="2"/> must be <term ref="#t182" type="subject">anti-nationalsocialist</term>. Both
					German and foreign <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> were generally allowed to <term ref="#t880" type="subject"
						>travel</term> earlier - so they could get rid of them -, but as the war progressed, another consideration became more and
					more applicable: The fear of <term ref="#t220" type="subject">information</term> about conditions in this country being spread
					across <term ref="#t213" type="subject">the world</term>, which could damage <term ref="#t1152" type="subject">Germany's</term>
					position and bring substance to the anti-<term ref="#t381" type="subject">nationalsocialist</term>
					<term ref="#t986" type="subject">propaganda</term>. It is therefore preferable not to see too much traffic across the borders, by
					persons who are not considered to be 100% <term ref="#t367" type="subject">reliable politically</term> – apart from the
					difficulties of permits for entry and exit in general - and for the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term>, who are all
					considered 100%-unreliable, we now see an almost completely shut down. While there are still exceptions made for foreign <term
						ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> it is no longer possible for German <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> to
					travel, even if they have acquired foreign <term ref="#t1147" type="subject">citizenship</term> by <term ref="#t375"
						type="subject">marriage</term>, especially when the marriage took place after the introduction of the Jewish law, which is the
					case both with the married couple Hagen and with marriage of Thomsen in Schøn’s letter of <date when="1942-08-01">7 August</date>
					to Ryder.</p>
				<p>As you know, in the first few years after the introduction of <term ref="#t335" type="subject">Jewish laws</term>, several <term
						ref="#t825" type="subject">female</term> German <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> married foreigners. The <term
						ref="#t1176" type="subject">German authorities</term> regard all these marriages as concluded solely for trying to circumvent
					the Jewish laws. In most cases, the motives behind the marriages are self-evident (which, of course, does not preclude the man
					from acting on the noblest and most humane <term ref="#t297" type="subject">motives</term>). In addition, according to <term
						ref="#t1152" type="subject">German</term> opinion, mixing <term ref="#t373" type="subject">Aryan</term> and <term ref="#t864"
						type="subject">Jewish</term> blood is a <term ref="#t365" type="subject">crime</term>, and that <term ref="#t375"
						type="subject">marriages</term> between <term ref="#t373" type="subject">Aryans</term> and <term ref="#t864" type="subject"
						>Jews</term> are <pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420910_03.jpg" n="3"/> forbidden. I, therefore, believe that we are wise to leave these
					cases as hopeless and save the very poor ‘goodwill’ we have for cases about <placeName ref="#kingdom-of-denmark"
						>Danish</placeName>
					<term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> with Connection to <placeName ref="#kingdom-of-denmark">Denmark</placeName>. Even for
					their part, it can be difficult, since the German side expects that the <term ref="#t948" type="subject">government</term> of a
					neighbouring country shows an <term ref="#t815" type="subject">understanding</term> of the German attitude, cf. Minister Mohr's
					Letter of <date when="1942-04-28">28 April</date> to the Director of the <orgName ref="#g006627">Ministry of Foreign
						Affairs</orgName> regarding Articles in the ' <term ref="#t711" type="subject">Kamptegnet</term> ', which in my opinion is
					very illustrative.</p>
				<p>The way in which you suggest allowing the Consulate General to go to the <term ref="#t1119" type="subject">police</term> has to be
					taken with great caution. In several cases, the police have <term ref="#t277" type="subject">rejected</term> such requests from
					the Consulate General and wanted the issue to go the <term ref="#t125" type="subject">diplomatic</term> way. We have also seen
					that the police authorities have said to the Consulate General that they would have to look after the person if she continued to
					bother them with applications. We hereby reach a point that I am afraid hasn’t had much <term ref="#t202" type="subject"
						>attention</term> at home. As a rule, the persons seeking our and the <orgName ref="#g006627">Ministry of Foreign
						Affairs`</orgName> assistance have tried all possible ways. The result easily becomes an Irritation to the Authorities, which
					may cause fatal consequences for the persons concerned. There is a risk that the authorities, in order to get rid of more
					nonsense, will <term ref="#t518" type="subject">send</term> those concerned to the <term ref="#t1191" type="subject">General
						Government</term> or to <placeName ref="#l29">Theresienstadt</placeName>. Furthermore, there is the risk of 1) that the
					relatively gentle treatment of foreign <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> in part is replaced by a sharper course and 2)
					that the question of precautionary <term ref="#t542" type="subject">measures</term> against <term ref="#t864" type="subject"
						>Jews</term> in <placeName ref="#kingdom-of-denmark">Denmark</placeName> becomes relevant. After all, <pb
						facs="EHRI-DR-19420910_04.jpg" n="4"/> it is of no use that <placeName ref="#kingdom-of-denmark">Denmark</placeName> becomes
					more famous than most necessary as a <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jewish</term> sanctuary. I, therefore, allow you to
					recommend that you explain to Mr. Hagen, that by pushing more on applications for the wife's exit permit, as well as through us as
					directly to the German authorities, will risk doing her more harm than good.</p>
				<p><persName ref="#ehri_dr_steensen-leth_vincens">Vincens Steensen-Leth</persName></p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
