<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://gitlab.inria.fr/dh-projects/workflow-ehri/-/raw/main/ODD/out/ODD-EHRI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="EHRI-DR-19411104a-US_EN" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title xml:lang="en">Franklin Mott Gunther on “Recent Developments in the Situation of the Jews in Rumania” in 1941</title>
				<principal><affiliation><orgName>European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</orgName></affiliation></principal>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>
					<ref target="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</ref>
				</authority>
				<availability>
					<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title ref="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">EHRI Edition of Diplomatic Reports</title>
			</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/countries/us">United States of America </country>
						<repository ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/institutions/us-005522">National Archives and Records Administration
							II</repository>
						<collection>National Archives and Records Administration II, RG 59, Records of the U. S. Department of State relating to
							internal affairs of Romania 1910-1944, Wilmington, Del. 1981 (Microfilm):</collection>
						<idno>Doc. 871.4016/287</idno>
					</msIdentifier>
					<physDesc/>
				</msDesc>
				<bibl>National Archives and Records Administration II, RG 59, Records of the U. S. Department of State relating to internal affairs of
					Romania 1910-1944, Wilmington, Del. 1981 (Microfilm): Doc. 871.4016/287, p. 2-4. Printed in FRUS 1941, vol. II, p. 871-874.
						<textLang mainLang="en">Original in English.</textLang></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation>
				<date when="1941-11-04">November 4, 1941</date>
				<placeName ref="#bucharest">Bucharest</placeName>
				<persName ref="#ehri_dr_gunther">Gunther, Franklin Mott Gunther</persName>
				<idno>EHRI-DR-19411104a-US</idno>
			</creation>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="transcription">
				<pb facs="R 6456-39 (134)" n="2"/>
				<p>The <orgName ref="#g003223">Department</orgName> is already aware that the <term ref="#t1036" type="subject">military
						occupation</term> of <placeName ref="#bessarabia">Bessarabia</placeName> and northern <placeName ref="#bukovina"
						>Bucovina</placeName> was followed by the <term ref="#t614" type="subject">establishment of Jews in ghettos</term> in the
					larger cities, and that large numbers, particularly from <placeName ref="#bessarabia">Bessarabia</placeName>, were gradually <term
						ref="#t623" type="subject">evacuated</term> into the territory lying beyond the <placeName ref="#dniester">Dniester
						River</placeName>. These <term ref="#t337" type="subject">measures</term> were carried out under appalling conditions and
					accompanied by innumerable kinds of frightfulness, including <term ref="#t660" type="subject">robbery</term>, <term ref="#t570"
						type="subject">starvation</term>, <term ref="#t532" type="subject">killings</term> and other brutalities. Only a relatively
					small number of <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> are believed now to be left in <placeName ref="#bessarabia"
						>Bessarabia</placeName> – estimates vary from ten to thirty thousand out of a total of just over two hundred thousand residing
					there prior to the <term ref="#t1036" type="subject">Russian seizure</term> of <placeName ref="#bessarabia">Bessarabia</placeName>
					in <date when="1940-06">June 1940</date> – while in <placeName ref="#bukovina">Bucovina</placeName> there are, according to
					reliable <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term>, some fifteen to twenty thousand <term ref="#t864" type="subject"
						>Jews</term> now awaiting <term ref="#t518" type="subject">deportation</term> eastward to <placeName ref="#transnistria"
						>Transnistria</placeName> and other parts of the <placeName ref="#ukraine">Ukraine</placeName>. A great many, undoubtedly tens
					of thousands, have already been thus <term ref="#t623" type="subject">evacuated</term>.</p>
				<pb facs="R 6456-39 (135)" n="3"/>
				<p>During the past three weeks evidence has been accumulating – first in the form of vague <term ref="#t852" type="subject"
						>rumors</term> and unconfirmed reports, then through increasingly substantial sources of information and finally in exchange
					of <term ref="#t843" type="subject">letters</term> between Marshal <persName ref="#p000010">Antonescu</persName> and the <term
						ref="#t892" type="subject">head</term> of the local <term ref="#t872" type="subject">Jewish community</term> – that such as
					remains of the <term ref="#t896" type="subject">Jewish population</term> in <placeName ref="#bukovina">Bucovina </placeName>and
						<placeName ref="#bessarabia">Bessarabia</placeName> is being <term ref="#t623" type="subject">evacuated</term> eastward into
					the war-devastated territory of the <placeName ref="#ukraine">Ukraine</placeName> under conditions so appalling that they would
					seem to afford a substantial share of the <term ref="#t623" type="subject">evacuees</term> little chance to <term ref="#t561"
						type="subject">survive</term>. Persistent reports have reached me daily regarding these unfortunate <term ref="#t1207"
						type="subject">people</term> – <term ref="#t826" type="subject">men</term>, <term ref="#t825" type="subject">women</term> and
						<term ref="#t824" type="subject">children</term>, including the old and ill – who, given only a few hours notice with the
					right to take with them only a meager ten kilograms of <term ref="#t887" type="subject">belongings</term> and the equivalent of
					two dollars in money – the <term ref="#t686" type="subject">stories</term> almost invariably add that these <term ref="#t887"
						type="subject">belongings</term> and the money are taken from them en route – have been herded eastward on foot or in carts or
					box-cars, to war-swept regions where buildings have been razed and <term ref="#t832" type="subject">food</term> and other <term
						ref="#t833" type="subject">supplies</term> destroyed or removed and where winter weather will soon prevail. This modern <term
						ref="#t616" type="subject">Captivity</term> would seem deliberately calculated to serve a program of virtual <term ref="#t529"
						type="subject">extermination</term> and, even if the persistent <term ref="#t852" type="subject">rumors</term> that the <term
						ref="#t623" type="subject">evacuees</term> in numberless cases are <term ref="#t655" type="subject">plundered</term> of their
						<term ref="#t887" type="subject">belongings</term>, that dozens and hundreds are <term ref="#t536" type="subject">shot</term>
					en route, pushed off bridges or dead of exhaustion, are greatly exaggerated or untrue, it seems certain that many thousands will
					perish. Of course, as suggested in the last paragraph of my telegram first cited above, many of these reports and <term
						ref="#t852" type="subject">rumors</term> are unconfirmed and must be classified as hearsay, or even <term ref="#t986"
						type="subject">propaganda</term> by interested persons [...] but I am bound to say that even the minimum of truth that I am
					sure lies in <pb facs="R 6456-39 (136)" n="4"/> these <term ref="#t686" type="subject">stories</term> is sufficient to give grave
						<term ref="#t173" type="subject">concern to the civilized world</term>.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
