<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://gitlab.inria.fr/dh-projects/workflow-ehri/-/raw/main/ODD/out/ODD-EHRI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="EHRI-DR-19390217-US_EN" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title xml:lang="en">George F. Kennan on antisemitic sentiments in Czechoslovakia in 1939</title>
				<principal><affiliation><orgName>European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</orgName></affiliation></principal>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>
					<ref target="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</ref>
				</authority>
				<availability>
					<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title ref="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">EHRI Edition of Diplomatic Reports</title>
			</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/countries/us">United States of America </country>
						<repository ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/institutions/us-005522">National Archives and Records Administration
							II</repository>
						<collection>RG 59 - Records of the Department of State relating to internal affairs of Czechoslovakia 1910-1944,
							Washington 1982 (Mikrofilm-Edition):</collection>
						<idno>Doc. 860F.4016/68</idno>
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
				<bibl>National Archives and Records Administration II, Records of the Department of State relating to internal affairs of
					Czechoslovakia 1910-1944, Washington 1982 (Mikrofilm-Edition), Doc. 860F.4016/68.<textLang mainLang="en"> Original in
						English.</textLang></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation>
				<date when="1939-02-17">February 17 1939</date>
				<placeName ref="#prague">Prague</placeName>
				<persName ref="#ehri_dr_Kennan_George_F.">Kennan, George F.</persName>
				<idno>EHRI-DR-19390217-US</idno></creation>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="transcription">
				<pb facs="EHRI-BF-19380906_01.jpg" n="1"/>
				<p>[...] Indeed, it is characteristic of <placeName ref="#cechy">Bohemia</placeName>, where <term ref="#t778" type="subject"
						>nationality</term>
					<pb facs="EHRI-BF-19380906_02.jpg" n="2"/> is a matter of language rather than of blood, that speech rather than origin is the
					distinguishing characteristic of friend or foe. Such resentment of the <term ref="#t896" type="subject">Jews</term> as exists in
						<placeName ref="#cechy">Bohemia</placeName> thus centers largely on the German-speaking <term ref="#t896" type="subject"
						>Jews</term> – particularly those who have come to <placeName ref="#cechy">Bohemia</placeName> since the <term ref="#t1080"
						type="subject">war</term>.</p>
				<p>Among the <placeName ref="#czechoslovakia">Czechs</placeName> themselves, there is comparatively little <term ref="#t329"
						type="subject">anti-semitism</term>. Only the small <placeName ref="#czechoslovakia">Czech</placeName>
					<term ref="#t964" type="subject">fascist groups</term> and certain sections of the <term ref="#t1017" type="subject"
						>nationalist</term>-<term ref="#t973" type="subject">conservative</term> element are <term ref="#t329" type="subject"
						>anti-semitic</term>. This applies particularly to the younger element in the <orgName
						ref="#ehri_dr_new_national_unitiy_party">New National Unity Party</orgName> , which is being organized as a <term ref="#t948"
						type="subject">government</term>
					<term ref="#t958" type="subject">party</term>. All these elements together, however, make up only a small <term ref="#t1062"
						type="subject">minority</term> of the <placeName ref="#czechoslovakia">Czech</placeName> population. The mass of the people
					appear simply to have very little interest in <term ref="#t329" type="subject">anti-semitism</term>.</p>
				<p>The present talk of <term ref="#t337" type="subject">anti-semitic measures</term> and the general <term ref="#t829" type="subject"
						>anxiety</term> of the <term ref="#t896" type="subject">Jewish population</term> is due principally to the pressure which is
					being brought to bear on the <placeName ref="#czechoslovakia">Czech</placeName>
					<term ref="#t948" type="subject">Government</term> by <placeName ref="#berlin">Berlin</placeName> in the direction of an <term
						ref="#t339" type="subject">anti-Jewish policy</term>. There is no doubt of the existence of this pressure. [...]</p>
				<p>Very little has happened in <placeName ref="#prague">Prague</placeName> thus far to justify the panicky atmosphere which has
					prevailed in <term ref="#t896" type="subject">Jewish circles</term> here since the Munich agreement. The vast majority of the
						<term ref="#t896" type="subject">Jews</term> in <placeName ref="#cechy">Bohemia</placeName> and <placeName ref="#moravia"
						>Moravia</placeName> have remained up to the present quite unmolested both in their private <pb facs="EHRI-BF-19380906_03.jpg"
						n="3"/> lives and their <term ref="#t918" type="subject">economic</term> activities. [...]</p>
				<p>In <placeName ref="#slovak-republic">Slovakia</placeName>, other conditions prevail. Here the percentage of <term ref="#t896"
						type="subject">Jews</term>, in the first place, is higher than in <placeName ref="#cechy">Bohemia</placeName>. The <placeName
						ref="#slovak-republic">Slovak</placeName>
					<term ref="#t896" type="subject">Jews</term> are not only prominent in the cities but, in contrast to the situation prevailing in
						<placeName ref="#cechy">Bohemia</placeName>, are scattered in large numbers throughout the countryside and play a conspicuous
					part in the <term ref="#t918" type="subject">economic life</term> of the <placeName ref="#slovak-republic">Slovak</placeName>
					village. They are the object of widespread resentment on the part of the <placeName ref="#slovak-republic">Slovak</placeName>
					population. Many of them are of the poorer <term ref="#t774" type="subject">orthodox</term> type. Their <term ref="#t836"
						type="subject">dress</term>, their manners and their habits are conspicuous and – to many <placeName ref="#slovak-republic"
						>Slovaks</placeName> – offensive. They are prominent in the villages as money-lenders, <term ref="#t899" type="subject"
						>lawyers</term>, saloon-keepers, druggists, merchants, etc. In the larger cities they form a wealthy class which makes up a
					good part of the <q>intelligentsia</q> and controls a very large proportion of the capital of the country.</p>
				<p>Many of the educated <term ref="#t896" type="subject">Jews</term> are <placeName ref="#hungary">Hungarian</placeName>-speaking and
					have always looked to <placeName ref="#budapest">Budapest</placeName> for <term ref="#t672" type="subject">cultural</term>
					inspiration. <pb facs="EHRI-BF-19380906_04.jpg" n="4"/> A smaller but by no means insignificant number have had a <placeName
						ref="#federal-republic-of-germany">German</placeName>
					<term ref="#t672" type="subject">cultural</term> orientation. This doubtless explains to a large extent the feeling prevalent in
					many <placeName ref="#slovak-republic">Slovak</placeName> circles to the effect that the <term ref="#t896" type="subject"
						>Jews</term> have always sided with the oppressors of the <placeName ref="#slovak-republic">Slovaks</placeName>, against the
						<term ref="#t637" type="subject">native population</term>. [...]</p>
				<pb facs="EHRI-BF-19380906_05.jpg" n="5"/>
				<p>As will have been seen from the above discussion, the <term ref="#t351" type="subject">Jewish question</term> in <placeName
						ref="#czechoslovakia">Czechoslovakia</placeName> presents a highly confused picture. The <term ref="#t896" type="subject"
						>Jews</term> themselves fall into many different categories, varying from the highly <term ref="#t672" type="subject"
						>cultured</term>
					<term ref="#t798" type="subject">intellectuals</term> of <placeName ref="#prague">Prague</placeName> to the pious and primitive
						<term ref="#t774" type="subject">orthodox</term>
					<term ref="#t896" type="subject">Jews</term> of the <placeName ref="#slovak-republic">Slovak</placeName> and Ruthenian villages.
					They are divided among various <term ref="#t672" type="subject">cultural</term> tendencies: Yiddish, <placeName
						ref="#federal-republic-of-germany">German</placeName>, <placeName ref="#hungary">Hungarian</placeName>, <placeName
						ref="#republic-of-poland">Polish</placeName> and <placeName ref="#czechoslovakia">Czechoslovak</placeName>. The <term
						ref="#t815" type="subject">attitude</term> of the <term ref="#t373" type="subject">Aryan</term> population toward them varies
					again, between city and country, between the various classes and professions, between the different provinces. In these
					circumstances, it is scarcely to be expected that any clear-cut <term ref="#t947" type="subject">policy</term> or <term
						ref="#t815" type="subject">attitude</term> on the part of the responsible authorities will emerge. It seems evident that if
						<placeName ref="#czechoslovakia">Czechoslovakia</placeName> existed in a vacuum the <term ref="#t896" type="subject"
						>Jews</term>, despite their considerable number, would not present any <ref
						target="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/vocabularies/ehri_terms/search?q=judenfrage">problem</ref> which could not be solved
					with relatively humane and painless <term ref="#t337" type="subject">methods</term>. The country does not contain in itself the
					basis for a really serious and widespread <term ref="#t352" type="subject">anti-semitic movement</term>.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
