<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://gitlab.inria.fr/dh-projects/workflow-ehri/-/raw/main/ODD/out/ODD-EHRI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="EHRI-DR-19420409-IT_EN" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title xml:lang="en">Paolo Cortese on the “Jewish Question” in Slovakia in 1942</title>
				<principal><affiliation><orgName>European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</orgName></affiliation></principal>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>
					<ref target="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</ref>
				</authority>
				<availability>
					<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title ref="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">EHRI Edition of Diplomatic Reports</title>
			</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/countries/it">Italy </country>
						<repository ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/institutions/it-002863">Archivio Storico Diplomatico del Ministero degli
							Affari Esteri</repository>
					</msIdentifier>
					<physDesc/>
				</msDesc>
				<bibl>Archivio Storico Diplomatico del Ministero degli Affari Esteri, AG. Uff. IV., Posizione S.E. 27.869, busta S, fasc. Slovacchia.
						<textLang mainLang="en">Original in Italian.</textLang></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation>
				<date when="1942-04-09">9.4.1942</date>
				<placeName ref="#bratislava">Bratislava</placeName>
				<persName ref="#ehri_dr_cortese_paolo">Cortese, Paolo</persName>
				<idno>EHRI-DR-19420409-IT</idno>
			</creation>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="transcription">
				<!--<p>EHRI-DR-19420409-IT_EN</p>
      <p>Report of the envoy in Bratislava, Paolo Cortese, to the Italian Foreign Ministry.</p>
      <p>Cable No. 1290/287</p>
      <p>R. Legation of Italy</p>-->
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420409-IT_01.jpg" n="1"/>
				<p>Addressed to Royal <orgName ref="#g005042">Ministry of Foreign Affairs</orgName>, Rome.</p>
				<p>Bratislava, 9th April 1942, Year XX</p>
				<p/>
				<p>Re: Jewish question</p>
				<p>The coldness with which the <placeName ref="#slovak-republic">Slovakian</placeName> Catholic <term ref="#t1068" type="subject"
						>press</term> has greeted the <term ref="#t337" type="subject">anti-Jewish action</term> of Minister of Interior <persName
						ref="#p000261">Mach</persName> is an indication of the mood of the <placeName ref="#slovak-republic">Slovakian</placeName>
					Catholic <term ref="#t637" type="subject">population</term> which, particularly in the provinces, <term ref="#t813" type="subject"
						>feels no ill</term> will towards <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> and because of their meekness and religious
					upbringing disagrees with the violent methods used by the men carrying out the expulsion decrees. There have even been instances
					in which local authorities have not carried out or carried out only partially the ministerial orders. As many as three prefects
					have been deposed or recalled and subjected to an enquiry. <term ref="#t767" type="subject">Church</term> authorities have also
					objected to the methods employed. It has been reported that the Minister of <placeName ref="#slovak-republic">Slovakia</placeName>
					to the <placeName ref="#state-of-the-vatican-city">Vatican</placeName> has been here, and there have been rumours about a note
					from the Secretariat of State to the <placeName ref="#slovak-republic">Slovakian</placeName> Legation. There has indeed been such
					a step and the Chargé d’Affaires of the Holy See here has repeatedly seen the <persName ref="#p000413">Prime Minister</persName>
					and Minister for Foreign Affairs on this issue. Also, there have been critical voices against <persName ref="#p000261"
						>Mach</persName> within the <term ref="#t948" type="subject">Government</term> itself, coming from his colleagues of the
						<orgName ref="#g471">Slovakian people’s party</orgName></p>
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420409-IT_02.jpg" n="2"/>
				<p>Nonetheless, the <term ref="#t518" type="subject">forced exodus</term> of <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> has
					continued and continues still. It is illegal, as no law authorizing it exists. There is – for now – only a <term ref="#t542"
						type="subject">bill</term> approved a few days ago by the Council of Minister which has still to be submitted to Parliament.
					The full powers granted by Parliament to the <term ref="#t948" type="subject">Government</term> in 1940 to proceed against <term
						ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> cannot possibly apply to the issue of the exodus. As I have learned from Minister
						<persName ref="#p000261">Mach</persName> himself, of the 90,000 <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> who were in
						<placeName ref="#slovak-republic">Slovakia</placeName> on 25th March last (in 1939 there were 120,000, 30,000 of whom have
					voluntarily left the country after the establishment of the independent Slovak State), 13,000 have been <term ref="#t518"
						type="subject">deported</term> these past weeks to the <placeName ref="#katowice">Katowice</placeName> area and to the
						<placeName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/units/de-002624-staatlakt-0_0-12-5">General Governorate</placeName> and those
					remaining will follow in the course of the next 6 months. <persName ref="#p000261">Mach</persName> told me “The <term ref="#t864"
						type="subject">Jews</term> were dominating our <term ref="#t918" type="subject">economy</term>”, and ended by saying that to
					remedy such a state of affairs, the time for half measures is over.</p>
				<p>When he was accused of having acted because forced to do so by the <term ref="#t1152" type="subject">Germans</term>, the <persName
						ref="#p000261">Minister of Interior</persName> declared to the <term ref="#t1068" type="subject">press</term>, as reported
					with Cable no. 1095/245 from <date when="1942-03-27">27th March</date>, that the expulsion of <term ref="#t864" type="subject"
						>Jews</term> had been decided “spontaneously and with full persuasion”.</p>
				<p>I have been told by the <term ref="#t1152" type="subject">German</term> Minister here that his <term ref="#t948" type="subject"
						>Government</term> had not used any pressure but had simply made a suggestion that had been accepted.</p>
				<p>As far as I know, the <persName ref="#p000789">President of the Republic</persName> has done his utmost to mitigate the harshness
					of the methods employed for the <term ref="#t518" type="subject">exodus</term> and made use, despite a strong <term ref="#t954"
						type="subject">opposition</term> from the <persName ref="#p000413">Prime Minister</persName> himself, of the right to
					discriminate granted him by the “Jewish Code” in order to save a great many persons from expulsion. Clearly, if <persName
						ref="#p000789">President Tiso</persName> has not done more and has even prevented a <term ref="#t1068" type="subject"
						>press</term> controversy on the <term ref="#t351" type="subject">Jewish question</term> from breaking out (all that appeared
					in the <term ref="#t1068" type="subject">press</term>, belatedly, were two critical articles in the Catholic <term ref="#t1069"
						type="subject">newspapers</term> Slovak and Slovenska Pravda), this is due to the fact that he finds himself unable to oppose
					the will of the <term ref="#t1152" type="subject">Reich</term>, which has in <persName ref="#p000413">Tuka</persName> and in
						<persName ref="#p000261">Mach</persName>, <pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420409-IT_03.jpg" n="3"/> particularly in regard to the <term
						ref="#t351" type="subject">Jewish question</term>, willing and convinced executors. It is also likely that Monsignor <persName
						ref="#p000789">Tiso</persName> judges that under any circumstances he can be more useful to his people in the presidential
					chair than elsewhere.</p>
				<p><persName ref="#ehri_dr_cortese_paolo">Cortese</persName></p>
				<p> </p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
