<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://gitlab.inria.fr/dh-projects/workflow-ehri/-/raw/main/ODD/out/ODD-EHRI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="EHRI-DR-19420508-IT_EN" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title xml:lang="en">Filippo Anfuso on antisemitism in Hungary in 1942</title>
				<principal><affiliation><orgName>European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</orgName></affiliation></principal>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>
					<ref target="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</ref>
				</authority>
				<availability>
					<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title ref="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">EHRI Edition of Diplomatic Reports</title>
			</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/countries/it">Italy</country>
						<repository ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/institutions/it-002863">Archivio Storico Diplomatico del Ministero degli
							Affari Esteri</repository>
					</msIdentifier>
					<physDesc/>
				</msDesc>
				<bibl>Archivio Storico Diplomatico del Ministero degli Affari Esteri, AG Uff IV., Posizione S.E. 27.869, busta T-U, fasc.
						Ungheria.<textLang mainLang="it"> Original in Italian.</textLang></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation>
				<date when="1942-05-08">8.5.1942</date>
				<placeName ref="www.geonames.org/3054643/budapest">Budapest</placeName>
				<persName ref="#ehri_dr_anfuso_filippo">Anfuso, Filippo</persName>
				<idno>EHRI-DR-19420508-IT</idno>
			</creation>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="transcription">
				<!--<p>EHRI-DR-19420508-IT_EN</p>
      <p>Report of the envoy in Budapest, <persName ref="#ehri_dr_anfuso_filippo">Filippo
          Anfuso</persName>, for the Italian Foreign Minister <persName
          ref="#p000082">Ciano</persName> of
          <date when="1942-05-08">8 May 1942</date>.</p>-->
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420508-IT_01.jpg" n="1"/>
				<p>To His Excellency</p>
				<p>Count Galeazzo <persName ref="#p000082">Ciano di Cortellazzo</persName></p>
				<p><orgName ref="#g006563">Minister of Foreign Affairs</orgName>, <placeName ref="#rome">Rome</placeName></p>
				<p><placeName ref="www.geonames.org/3054643/budapest">Budapest</placeName>, <date when="1942-05-08">8th May 1942</date>, XX</p>
				<p>Re: Semitism and <term ref="#t329" type="subject">anti-Semitism</term> in <placeName ref="#hungary">Hungary</placeName>.</p>
				<p>Sir,</p>
				<p>The program of <term ref="#t335" type="subject">anti-Jewish policy</term> outlined by President <persName ref="#p000202"
						>Kállay</persName> in his speeches to the Lower Chamber and to the Party’s National Council (<date when="1942-03-20">20th
						March</date> and <date when="1942-04-20">20th April</date> last) and the measures that followed represent the start of a new
					stage in <placeName ref="#hungary">Hungary</placeName>’s official <term ref="#t329" type="subject">anti-Semitism</term>. This R.
					Legation has repeatedly reported on the various developments and on individual aspects of the <term ref="#t351" type="subject"
						>Jewish problem</term> in this Country, highlighting along the way the various obstacles that have hindered the implementation
					of radical <term ref="#t335" type="subject">measures</term>, the conflicting opinions within the Country, the <term ref="#t731"
						type="subject">Clergy</term> and Parliament on the issue of <term ref="#t542" type="subject">anti-Jewish legislation</term>,
					and on the frequent compromises ensuing from the doubts of a <term ref="#t1072" type="subject">public opinion</term> at times
					unconvinced that a drastic action is wise. However, the general situation in which the <term ref="#t351" type="subject">Jewish
						problem</term> now again surfaces on the <placeName ref="#hungary">Hungarian</placeName>
					<term ref="#t947" type="subject">political scene</term> has changed deeply since the day when <placeName ref="#hungary"
						>Hungary</placeName>, linking its destiny to that of the <term ref="#t1027" type="subject">Axis Powers</term>, necessarily had
					to do away, even in its interior <term ref="#t1027" type="subject">politics</term>, with many hesitations and many formal
					shackles. Herein lies precisely the interest that the <term ref="#t351" type="subject">Jewish problem</term> continues to attract
					after the <pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420508-IT_02.jpg" n="2"/> emphatic and formally definitive official stance taken by the present
						<term ref="#t948" type="subject">Government</term>. <q>We will not desist from the struggle – said <persName ref="#p000202"
							>Kállay</persName> – until with a systematic and ever increasing pace we have taken away from the <term ref="#t864"
							type="subject">Jews</term> every sector of national life and we have at last entirely removed them from our Country.</q>
					In order to appreciate the significance of these words and to understand the complexity of the situation to which they refer it
					might be worthwhile to briefly reconsider the fundamental aspects of the <term ref="#t351" type="subject">Jewish problem</term> in
						<placeName ref="#hungary">Hungary</placeName>.</p>
				<p>Among the other misfortunes which befell this Country at the time of the <placeName ref="#republic-of-turkey">Turkish</placeName>
					invasion there was also the influx of many <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> who found a favourable situation under the
					Crescent. The expulsion of the <term ref="#ehri_dr_nationalities_turkish" type="subject">Turks</term> caused most of them to
					leave. Later, the severe decrees of the Habsburgs, particularly <persName ref="#ehri_dr_charles_iii">Charles III</persName> and
						<persName ref="#ehri_dr_maria_theresa">Maria Theresa</persName>, helped to keep the <term ref="#t864" type="subject"
						>Jews</term> away from <placeName ref="#hungary">Hungary</placeName>. Between <date when="1820">1820</date> and <date
						when="1830">1830</date>, however, there began that exodus of <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> from <placeName
						ref="#galicia">Galicia</placeName> to the <placeName ref="#hungary">Hungarian</placeName> territory which would continue
					uninterrupted into our own times, encouraged by the rise of capitalism and by the policies of the liberal <term ref="#t948"
						type="subject">governments</term> that enabled the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> to acquire predominance
					particularly in <term ref="#t708" type="subject">culture</term> and in the <term ref="#t816" type="subject">economy</term>. The
					census of <date when="1930">1930</date> registered 444,565 <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> then present in <placeName
						ref="#hungary">Hungary</placeName>, to whom one must add 78,190 in Upper Hungary (First <pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420508-IT_03.jpg"
						n="3"/> Vienna Award), 103,000 in Subcarpathia and 148,288 in <placeName ref="#transilvania">Transylvania</placeName> (Second
					Vienna Award). Today there are approx. 800,000 <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> living in <placeName ref="#hungary"
						>Hungary</placeName>, that is about 6.2 % of the <placeName ref="#hungary">Hungarian</placeName> population (13,500,000), a
					percentage that within Europe is exceeded only by <placeName ref="#republic-of-poland">Poland</placeName>, by <placeName
						ref="#republic-of-lithuania">Lithuania</placeName> and perhaps by <placeName ref="#romania">Romania</placeName>. In the
						<placeName ref="#budapest">capital</placeName> only (1,110,000) the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> are over
					200,000 and have attained preeminent positions in <term ref="#t891" type="subject">banking</term>, in <term ref="#t890"
						type="subject">manufacturing</term>, in commerce, in <term ref="#t712" type="subject">journalism</term> and in the <term
						ref="#t671" type="subject">arts</term>. Even the Hungarian aristocracy, which together with the great landowning middle
					classes has for centuries held the leadership of the Country and has controlled it politically, has been unable or unwilling to
					oppose this invasion and in the end even acquiesced to it through a great many <term ref="#t375" type="subject">marriages</term>
					that proved eminently useful to the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> for strengthening their position in <term
						ref="#t983" type="subject">political life</term>. The numerous Liberal-<term ref="#t1204" type="subject">Masonic</term>
					associations which emerged in <placeName ref="#hungary">Hungary</placeName> in the second half of the past century and the <term
						ref="#t1020" type="subject">Democratic Party</term>, which immediately became the only workers’ party with a western-style
					organization, formed the framework which protected <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jewish</term> activity and the breeding ground
					both of the democratic revolution of <date when="1918-10">October 1918</date> and of the <term ref="#t1009" type="subject"
						>Communist</term> revolution of <date when="1919-03">March 1919</date>.</p>
				<p>Statistics show better than any discourse the extent of the <term ref="#t872" type="subject">Jewish</term> invasion into <placeName
						ref="#hungary">Hungarian</placeName> life. If we limit our analysis to <placeName ref="#budapest">Budapest</placeName>, which
					sums up the general situation, we will find the following percentages in <date when="1935">1935</date>: bankers 80%; transport
					70%; stockbrokers 76%; <pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420508-IT_04.jpg" n="4"/> jewellers 74%; typographers 73%; owners of public
					establishments 57%; <term ref="#t899" type="subject">lawyers</term> 52%; <term ref="#t1427" type="subject">doctors</term> 40%;
						<term ref="#t712" type="subject">journalists</term> 35%.</p>
				<p>In the country, only 10% of the great landowners (over 100 Jugers) are <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term>, but among the
					tenants of great properties the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> number 42%. As for the manufacturing sector, the
					presence of <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> is shown by the following numbers: iron and steel 50%, machinery 43%,
					timber 53%, leather 68%, textiles 66%, clothing 73%, paper 58%, chemistry 54%, etc.</p>
				<p>After the fall of the <persName ref="#p000570">Bethlen</persName> Cabinet (<date when="1932">1932</date>), whose policy had greatly
					facilitated <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jewish</term> intrusiveness, the <persName ref="#p001073">Gömbös</persName>
					<term ref="#t948" type="subject">Government</term> marked the beginning of a <term ref="#t212" type="subject">resistance</term>
					movement, solicited and demanded by the emergent far right organizations that were increasingly exerting their influence on the
						<persName ref="#p000555">Daranyi</persName>, <persName ref="#p000191">Imredi </persName> etc. <term ref="#t948" type="subject"
						>governments</term> that came later. The first <term ref="#t335" type="subject">anti-Jewish law</term> dates from <date
						when="1938-04">April 1938</date>. The text avoided the word “<term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term>” and granted such
					ample <term ref="#t332" type="subject">discrimination</term> as to leave almost unaltered the average presence of <term
						ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> in the different sectors of <placeName ref="#hungary">Hungarian</placeName> life. The
					pressure exerted by the rightist <term ref="#t958" type="subject">parties</term> and the repercussions from the international
					situation prompted the second <term ref="#t335" type="subject">Jewish law</term> in <date when="1938-12">December 1938</date>,
					whose fundamental principles are derived from the <placeName ref="#italian-republic">Italian</placeName>
					<term ref="#t335" type="subject">anti-Jewish law</term> of <date when="1938-11-10">10th November 1939</date> [sic!, actually 1938]
					and which, in determining the definition of <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jew</term> according to fundamentally racial
					criteria, contains – numerous exceptions notwithstanding – severe measures. The <term ref="#t332" type="subject">law</term>
					<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420508-IT_05.jpg" n="5"/> reduces voting rights to a minimum, excludes <term ref="#t864" type="subject"
						>Jews</term> from the Lower Chamber; limits the presence of <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> in secondary schools,
					in universities and in professional associations to 6%, excludes <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> from the editorship
					of dailies and periodicals, from the directorship of <term ref="#t695" type="subject">theatres</term> and cinemas, etc. A later
						<term ref="#t335" type="subject">law</term> of <date when="1941-10">October 1941</date> forbade <term ref="#t375"
						type="subject">marriage</term> between <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> and non-Jews and punished severely any
						<term ref="#t838" type="subject">sexual intercourse</term> between Jewish men and <term ref="#t373" type="subject"
						>Aryan</term> “honest women”. Lastly, after further measures concerning implementation procedures, the <persName
						ref="#p000202">Kállay</persName> Government, which came to power in <date when="1942-03">March 1942</date>, has decreed the
						<term ref="#t585" type="subject">confiscation</term> of all Jewish landed and wooded property (this R. Legation’s report no.
					742/374 of 20th March last ) and the definitive exclusion of <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> from the exploitation of
					national soil. The latest decree of considerable importance is the one approved by the Chamber on <date when="1942-05-01">1st
						May</date>, which rules that as from that date the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jewish</term> persuasion ceases to be
					officially acknowledged by the <placeName ref="#hungary">Hungarian state</placeName>.</p>
				<p>Some facts emerge from what has been said here that place the <placeName ref="#hungary">Hungarian</placeName>
					<term ref="#t351" type="subject">Jewish problem</term> in its true perspective.</p>
				<p>First of all, the main factor that encouraged the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jewish</term> invasion in <placeName
						ref="#hungary">Hungary</placeName> and is still far from having vanished needs to be pointed out. I mean the absence, in the
					social structure of this Country, of an urban middle class that might carry out the functions and the tasks that have been taken
					over by the <pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420508-IT_06.jpg" n="6"/>
					<term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term>. This explains why it is fairly easy to implement the <term ref="#t335"
						type="subject">anti-Jewish law</term> in the countryside, where the aristocracy and the landed middle classes are still active
					and significant forces, whereas it remains difficult to do the same in the towns and particularly in <placeName ref="#budapest"
						>Budapest</placeName>, where the immediate removal, supposing it were possible to carry it out, of all <term ref="#t864"
						type="subject">Jews</term> holding managing posts in <term ref="#t937" type="subject">industry</term>, commerce and <term
						ref="#t930" type="subject">banks</term> would cause a crisis that would overwhelm the Hungarian economy. Only by gradually and
					simultaneously inserting <placeName ref="#hungary">Hungarian</placeName> elements that are capable of <term ref="#t674"
						type="subject">occupying</term> the posts at present held by <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> will <placeName
						ref="#hungary">Hungary</placeName> be able to face the actual expulsions of the latter from the most vital hubs of its
					economic structure. This necessity highlights another delicate aspect of the problem. As long as it is not able to replace them,
						<placeName ref="#hungary">Hungary</placeName> cannot do without the, albeit limited, cooperation of the <term ref="#t864"
						type="subject">Jews</term>, yet at the same time cannot be in doubt as to the state of mind of this by no means insignificant
					part of its population and as to the influence it has on <term ref="#t1072" type="subject">public opinion</term>. This is why,
					since an immediate and complete solution of the problem looks impossible, the Hungarian Government intends to continue to keep the
						<term ref="#t351" type="subject">Jewish question</term> alive and open; its final conclusion, as President <persName
						ref="#p000202">Kalláy</persName> said in his latest speech, will be removal outside of <placeName ref="#hungary"
						>Hungary</placeName> of all the 800,000 <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> living in the Country.</p>
				<p>As I already said, the numerous <term ref="#t375" type="subject">mixed marriages</term> entered into by the <term ref="#t864"
						type="subject">Jews</term> served them well in strengthening their position in <placeName ref="#hungary">Hungary</placeName>.
					Moreover, <pb facs="EHRI-DR-19420508-IT_07.jpg" n="7"/> it cannot be ignored that in joining their power to that of many
					aristocratic and middle class families, the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> of <placeName ref="#hungary"
						>Hungary</placeName> have created a network of shared interests and of solidarity with the very social classes that ought to
					fight them. And they have contributed not a little to the spreading of the liberal ideology, which in this Country is perhaps more
					enduring than in others.</p>
				<p>The solution of the <term ref="#t351" type="subject">Jewish problem</term> therefore poses for <placeName ref="#hungary"
						>Hungary</placeName> a distressful and difficult problem as it closely concerns its social structure and its economic
					organization, and this, moreover, at a time when the Country needs all its energies to face its new and important tasks. This
					explains the hesitancy apparent in the past in the Government’s <term ref="#t337" type="subject">anti-Jewish action</term> and a
					certain scepticism displayed even today by many towards the effectiveness and even towards the sincerity of the Government’s <term
						ref="#t335" type="subject">anti-Jewish policies</term>, But the Government’s will to advance on the road it has in part
					already covered does not appear in doubt and it may not be unnecessary to point out that considerations and influences of an <term
						ref="#t1021" type="subject">international nature</term> are not without bearing on this will.</p>
				<p>Please accept, Sir, the expression of my profound respect.</p>
				<p><persName ref="#ehri_dr_filippo_anfuso">Anfuso</persName></p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
