<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://gitlab.inria.fr/dh-projects/workflow-ehri/-/raw/main/ODD/out/ODD-EHRI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="EHRI-DR-19430314-IT_EN" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title xml:lang="en">Guelfo Zamboni on the measures against Jews in Thessaloniki in 1943</title>
				<principal><affiliation><orgName>European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</orgName></affiliation></principal>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>
					<ref target="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</ref>
				</authority>
				<availability>
					<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title ref="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">EHRI Edition of Diplomatic Reports</title>
			</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/countries/it">Italy </country>
						<repository ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/institutions/it-002863">Archivio Storico Diplomatico del Ministero degli
							Affari Esteri</repository>
					</msIdentifier>
				</msDesc>
				<bibl>Archivio Storico Diplomatico del Ministero degli Affari Esteri, Consolato generale Salonicco, busta 84, fasc. Misure razziali.
					Pratiche varie. <textLang mainLang="it"> Original in Italian.</textLang></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation>
				<date when="1943-05-14">14.3.1943</date>
				<placeName ref="#thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</placeName>
				<persName ref="#ehri_dr_zamboni_guelfo">Zamboni, Guelfo</persName>
				<idno>EHRI-DR-19430314-IT</idno>
			</creation>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="transcription">
				<!--<p>EHRI-DR-19430314-IT_EN</p>
      <p>Report of the Italian <term ref="#t1118"
          type="subject">Consul General</term> in <placeName
          ref="#thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</placeName>, <persName
          ref="#ehri_dr_zamboni_guelfo">Guelfo Zamboni</persName>, of EHRI-DR-19430314-IT_EN to the Italian Representation in
          <placeName ref="#hellenic-republic"
        >Greece</placeName>.</p>
      <p>[Carbon Copy]</p>
      <p>no. 1085/151</p>
      <p>no. 1086/318</p>-->
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19430314-IT_01.jpg" n="1"/>
				<p>R. Representation of <placeName ref="#italian-republic">Italy</placeName> for <placeName ref="#hellenic-republic"
						>Greece</placeName>, <placeName ref="#athens">Athens</placeName></p>
				<p>c.c.</p>
				<p>R. <orgName ref="#g005042">Ministry of Foreign Affairs</orgName>, <placeName ref="#rome">Rome</placeName></p>
				<p>Classified</p>
				<p><date when="1943-05-14">14th March 1943</date>,</p>
				<p>Class./<term ref="#t330" type="subject">Measures</term> against the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> of <placeName
						ref="#thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</placeName>.</p>
				<p>The Jews of Thessaloniki have been entirely <term ref="#t332" type="subject">excluded from any activity</term> and have for over a
					week now been confined to the <term ref="#t545" type="subject">ghetto</term>, unable <term ref="#t335" type="subject">to
						leave</term> it for any reason whatsoever.</p>
				<p>Their entire <term ref="#t333" type="subject">property has been seized</term> and will be managed through <term ref="#t590"
						type="subject">fiduciaries</term>, who will have to deposit the proceeds from sales in a special blocked account. So far it is
					not precisely known if part of the sums thus obtained will be used for the sustenance of <term ref="#t888" type="subject"
						>destitute Jews</term>, who are the great majority.</p>
				<p>Several sources confirm that their <term ref="#t575" type="subject">transfer</term> to <placeName ref="#republic-of-poland"
						>Poland</placeName> should start anytime now.</p>
				<p><term ref="#t1032" type="subject">German authorities</term> have requested from the <term ref="#t872" type="subject">Jewish
						Community</term> a list of 120 prominent persons to be regarded as hostages. In this list there are also 12 Italian citizens
					of <term ref="#t365" type="subject">Jewish race</term> who, together with the others, were summoned on the 7th inst. to the <term
						ref="#t872" type="subject">Community`s</term> premises where a German officer gave a short speech and explained that they
					would answer with their own persons for any accident or <term ref="#t246" type="subject">act of sabotage</term> that might occur.
					He added that it would have been his duty to intern them at once in a <term ref="#t496" type="subject">concentration camp</term>,
					but that due to the assurances given by the Chief <term ref="#t735" type="subject">Rabbi</term> he would let them stay free for
					the time being. The said prominent persons are also required to provide out of their own means for the needs of the poorer <term
						ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term>.</p>
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19430314-IT_02.jpg" n="2"/>
				<p>I have approached the <term ref="#t1084" type="subject">Befehlshaber</term> and was able to obtain his assurance that the Italian
					citizens will be removed from said list and we reached an understanding that they will no longer comply with <term ref="#t339"
						type="subject">the instructions and the orders</term> they should still receive through the <term ref="#t872" type="subject"
						>Jewish Community</term>.</p>
				<p>Due to the zeal displayed by the offices in charge of carrying out the <term ref="#t330" type="subject">adopted measures</term>, I
					find myself compelled all the time to undertake steps to prevent our fellow-citizens from being hampered in their usual commercial
					activity. Until now, however, there have been only inevitable repercussions of a very limited and modest relevance.</p>
				<p>The sudden removal from town life of over 50 thousand people, who for centuries had continuously been engaged in <term ref="#t864"
						type="subject">important activities</term>, has been the cause of serious inconveniences. A great many services that were
					provided almost <term ref="#t889" type="subject">exclusively by Jews</term> are now missing, and the price of commodities has
					increased sharply, to the point where the local <term ref="#t1068" type="subject">press</term> has been clamouring for severe
					steps against the <placeName ref="#hellenic-republic">Greek</placeName> merchants who exploit the present moment.</p>
				<p>Due to the closing of the great many <term ref="#t890" type="subject">Jewish shops</term>, to the diminished traffic in the streets
					and to the scarcity of public in cinemas and in restaurants-cafés, the town has acquired a look pervaded by a sense of
					sadness.</p>
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19430314-IT_03.jpg" n="3"/>
				<p>The <placeName ref="#hellenic-republic">Greek</placeName> element, except for the merchants who have seen their dreaded competitors
					disappear, displays no enthusiasm for all that is being done, quite the opposite, they worry about the immediate and future
					consequences.</p>
				<p>The <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> who had been <term ref="#t338" type="subject">issued by us with a pass</term> have
					been prevented by <term ref="#t1152" type="subject">German</term> authorities from reaching our zone. I have enquired to see if
					some exception might not be granted for the most serious cases, but have received a <term ref="#t1033" type="subject">negative
						answer</term>, in fact I was told that they would request that those who had already moved into our territory be returned to
					them.</p>
				<p>(<persName ref="#ehri_dr_zamboni_guelfo">Guelfo Zamboni</persName> )</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
