<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://gitlab.inria.fr/dh-projects/workflow-ehri/-/raw/main/ODD/out/ODD-EHRI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="EHRI-DR-19431111-DK_EN" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title xml:lang="en"> Unknown author on "The Jewish Question in Germany" in 1943</title>
				<principal><affiliation><orgName>European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</orgName></affiliation></principal>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>
					<ref target="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</ref>
				</authority>
				<availability>
					<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title ref="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">EHRI Edition of Diplomatic Reports</title>
			</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/countries/dk">Denmark</country>
						<repository ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/institutions/dk-002313"> Rigsarkivet Danish National Archives </repository>
					</msIdentifier>
					<physDesc/>
				</msDesc>
				<bibl>Rigsarkivet, 140. N. 33a, Gruppeordnede sager. <textLang mainLang="en">Original in Danish.</textLang></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation>
				<date when="1943-11-01">01.11.1943</date>
				<placeName ref="#copenhagen">Copenhagen</placeName><idno>EHRI-DR-19431111-DK</idno>
			</creation>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="transcription">
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19431025_01.jpg" n="1"/>
				<p>The <term ref="#t351" type="subject">Jewish question</term> in <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/maps/wikipedia_52.5167_13.4"
						>Germany</placeName>.</p>
				<p>During the period from spring 1940 to Spring 1943, the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> in Germany were <term
						ref="#t518" type="subject">deported</term>. The <term ref="#t518" type="subject">deportation</term> began in <placeName
						ref="#szczecin">Stettin</placeName> in <date when="1940-02">February 1940</date> and is now largely completed, so that all the
					elderly (originally over 65, now over 70 years) came to <placeName ref="#l29">Theresienstadt</placeName> in the <ref
						target="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/admindistricts-212">Bohemia-Moravian Protectorate</ref>, whose former
					population had been <term ref="#t1173" type="subject">evacuated</term>. The city, which originally had 20 to 25,000 inhabitants,
					now contains approx. 50,000 <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term>. However, because of the fact that the population
					consists only of the Old people, the passing is still very large. Young <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> have been
					deployed to <term ref="#t488" type="subject">work</term> in various locations in the eastern areas. The deportation has been
					practiced somewhat differently in the different regions of <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/maps/wikipedia_52.5167_13.4"
						>Germany</placeName>.</p>
				<p>The exceptions that apply to certain areas of the <term ref="#t337" type="subject">measures</term> against the <term ref="#t864"
						type="subject">Jews</term> under the legislation, with regard to <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> married to <term
						ref="#t373" type="subject">Aryans</term>, have not been fully observed during the Deportations. The Jewish spouse in such a
						<term ref="#t375" type="subject">marriage</term> is usually spared only when he or she lives with the <term ref="#t373"
						type="subject">Aryan partner</term> or with any <term ref="#t374" type="subject">common Children</term>, as a rule, there is
					no difference as to whether the children are minors or adults.</p>
				<p>Thus, there are several cases where Jewish men married to <term ref="#t373" type="subject">Aryan</term> women have been deported,
					however, there are no cases where Jewish women married to <term ref="#t373" type="subject">Aryan</term> men were deported. There
					must also have been cases in which the Jewish spouse has been deported after the <term ref="#t375" type="subject">couple's</term>
					only son has <term ref="#t1086" type="subject">fallen</term> in the war, which otherwise <term ref="#t365" type="subject">in
						Jewish laws</term> justifies a privileged position. This is motivated by the fact that the <term ref="#t520" type="subject"
						>exception from deportation</term> can only be justified on the grounds of the spouse or children, and that this consideration
					no longer applies when the child does not live at home, cf. above, or has fallen in the war.</p>
				<p>Although <term ref="#t365" type="subject">Jewish law</term> in principle applies only to <term ref="#t864" type="subject"
						>Jews</term>, there are so many special provisions in the <term ref="#t581" type="subject">Practice of Mischlinge</term>
						(<term ref="#t374" type="subject">Half and Quarter Jews</term>) that they must be regarded as a special class. In addition, in
					all areas where the Administration’s decisions are decisive, the principle of the <term ref="#t329" type="subject">anti-Jewish
						attitude</term> must be considered. <pb facs="EHRI-DR-19431025_02.jpg" n="2"/> Within leading circles, there are two
					movements, one that wants to restrict the <term ref="#t365" type="subject">Jewish laws</term> to the real <term ref="#t864"
						type="subject">Jews</term>, and one more radical that wants to <term ref="#t349" type="subject">liberate</term> Germany from
					both <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> and <q><term ref="#t374" type="subject">Bastards</term></q>.</p>
				<p>Which movement ultimately prevails is impossible to say, but the radical direction in recent times seems to assert itself, in
					particular, the provision introduced in 1942, whereby <term ref="#t374" type="subject">half Jews</term> are <term ref="#t664"
						type="subject">excluded</term> from the army, could be fatal. One has to consider, that the definition of the concept of <term
						ref="#t1147" type="subject">citizenship</term> links to the right to exercise <term ref="#t1059" type="subject">civil
						rights</term> such as <term ref="#t1086" type="subject">military service</term> and labor service. Therefore <term ref="#t374"
						type="subject">Mischlinge</term>, who fail to serve, are <term ref="#t659" type="subject">prevented from enjoying civil
						rights</term>.</p>
				<p>[…]</p>
				<p>Despite the fact that there is no prohibition in the <term ref="#t365" type="subject">Legislature</term> of <term ref="#t374"
						type="subject">Quarter Jews</term> marrying non-Jews, the <q><orgName ref="#ehri_dr_standesamt">Standesämter</orgName></q>
					refuse to marry such persons unless there is a special permit.</p>
				<p>The limited access of the <term ref="#t374" type="subject">Mischlinge</term> to - in the case of <term ref="#t374" type="subject"
						>Half Jews</term>, total exclusion from - the <term ref="#t842" type="subject">higher education</term> (including vocational
					schools) may in the future have the most fateful consequences, with <term ref="#t374" type="subject">Half Jews</term> subsequently
					missing the prerequisite for becoming anything but unskilled <term ref="#t902" type="subject">workers</term>.</p>
				<p><term ref="#t374" type="subject">Mischlinge</term> are excluded from owning an <term ref="#t946" type="subject">inheritance
						farm</term>, requiring <term ref="#t627" type="subject">Aryan descent since 1800</term>. With regard to other land estates,
					there is no prohibition, but in practice, <term ref="#t374" type="subject">Mischlinge</term> will generally be <term ref="#t333"
						type="subject">forced out</term> of possession of such property, the same applies to non-Jewish spouses of <term ref="#t864"
						type="subject">Jews</term>.</p>
				<p><term ref="#t375" type="subject">Mischlinge and non-Jewish spouses</term> have free access to private businesses. Another thing is
					that in Practice they will often be <term ref="#t585" type="subject">pushed out</term> of <term ref="#t924" type="subject"
						>Companies</term> of any significance, especially in the <term ref="#t938" type="subject">armour industry</term> – companies
					owned them or within which they play a large role will be excluded from public order.</p>
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19431025_03.jpg" n="3"/>
				<p>There are still <term ref="#t852" type="subject">rumours</term> in <placeName ref="#berlin">Berlin</placeName> of further <term
						ref="#t337" type="subject">measures taken against the Jews</term>, e.g., it states that a <term ref="#t582" type="subject"
						>law</term> must be drawn up, requiring <term ref="#t347" type="subject">Aryans</term> who are married to <term ref="#t864"
						type="subject">Jews</term> to divorce. After that, the <term ref="#t365" type="subject">Jewish law</term> in its full extent
					could be put into effect also for the group of <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> who have hitherto been allowed to stay
					because they were married to <term ref="#t373" type="subject">Aryans</term>. Furthermore, <term ref="#t852" type="subject"
						>rumours</term> have been spread regarding certain measures against <term ref="#t374" type="subject">half Jews</term>. In
					particular, it is said that <term ref="#t374" type="subject">Mischlinge</term> in cities, where the housing demand is high due to
					the devastation caused by <term ref="#t1083" type="subject">airstrikes</term>, should be evicted from their <term ref="#t660"
						type="subject">apartments</term>. Whether this will happen is impossible to predict. However, with some anxiety, it has been
					noted that the <term ref="#t342" type="subject">Campaign</term> against the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> in the
						<term ref="#t341" type="subject">Press</term> has now been intensified again. However, for the first time, lately, <term
						ref="#t347" type="subject">Mischlinge</term> has been referred to as <q>Bastards</q>. The fact that the <term ref="#t581"
						type="subject">Mischling problem</term> is to a significant degree an upper-class problem; since the <term ref="#t375"
						type="subject">mixed marriages</term> have mainly taken place within the bourgeoisie, there could also be an unfortunate
					impact on the position of the <term ref="#t374" type="subject">Mischlinge</term>.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
