<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/EHRI/ehri-online-editions/main/ODD/out/ODD_EHRI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="EHRI-DR-19391109-DK_EN" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title xml:lang="en">Eigil Leth on the Conditions of Jews in the Protectorate of Bohemia and Moravia in 1939</title>
				<title xml:lang="de">Eigil Leth über die Lage der Juden im Protektorat Böhmen und Mähren im Jahr 1939</title>
				<principal><affiliation><orgName>European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</orgName></affiliation></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Edited by</resp>
					<orgName>EHRI Edition of Diplomatic Reports</orgName>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>
					<ref target="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</ref>
				</authority>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title>Diplomatic Reports</title>
			</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<institution><orgName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/institutions/dk-002313"> Rigsarkivet Danish National Archives </orgName><address>
								<street>Rigsdagsgaarden 9</street>
								<postCode>DK-1218</postCode>
								<settlement>Copenhagen</settlement>
								<country ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/countries/dk">Denmark</country>
							</address></institution>
					</msIdentifier>
					<physDesc/>
				</msDesc>
				<bibl>Rigsarkivet, Depecher 1848-1972, Berlin 1939. <textLang mainLang="en">Original in Danish.</textLang></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p xml:lang="fr">L'encodage de ce document s'est fait dans le cadre du travail sur les éditions en ligne EHRI</p>
				<p xml:lang="en">The encoding of this document is part of the work on the EHRI Online Editions</p>
				<p xml:lang="de">Die Kodierung dieses Dokuments ist Teil der Arbeit an den EHRI Online Editions</p>
			</projectDesc>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation>
				<origDate when="1939-11-09">11.9.1939</origDate>
				<origPlace ref="http://www.geonames.org/2950159/berlin.html">Berlin</origPlace>
				<persName ref="#ehri_dr_leth_eigil">Leth, Eigil</persName>
			</creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="da"/>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2024-05-27" who="#floriane.chiffoleau">Upgrading TEI encoding</change>
			<change when-iso="2021" who="#ehri">Encoding of the file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="transcription">
				<div type="original">
					<p>The original transcription is not available.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="translation">
					<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19391109_01.jpg" n="1"/>
					<p>Mr. <orgName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_cb-006627">Foreign Minister</orgName></p>
					<p>I have the honour of forwarding the 3 copies of the confidential report received from the Royal. Consul General in <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/3067696/prague.html">Prague</placeName>. Dated the 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi>. concerning - the Conditions of the <placeName
							ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/terezin-places-place-iti-64">Protectorate of Bohemia and Moravia</placeName>. I have the honour to remain with the highest consideration</p>
					<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19391109_02.jpg" n="2"/>
					<p>Dear Chamberlain <persName ref="#ehri_dr_zahle_herluf">Zahle</persName></p>
					<p>The situation has worsened considerably, since 21 September of the same year, when I last reported about the conditions here. By the messages I have received I am under the impression that the <ref target="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/admindistricts-212">State
							Protector</ref> and several of his officials sincerely wanted to establish a good relationship between <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2921044/federal-republic-of-germany.html">Germans</placeName> and <placeName ref="#ehri_dr_nationalities_czechs"
							>Czechs</placeName>. However, the <orgName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_cb-407">party</orgName> with the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/maps/wikipedia_50.7361_15.74.html">Sudeten</placeName> German Secretary of State, Mr. <persName
							ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_pers-000124">Frank</persName> at the helm have completely lacked the tact needed or they may have thought that with hardness one should suppress any <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-212"
							type="subject">resistance</term> from the <placeName ref="#ehri_dr_nationalities_czechs">Czechs</placeName>.</p>
					<p>Now you can see a <orgName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_cb-671">Germanization</orgName> of the <placeName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/terezin-places-place-iti-64">Protectorate</placeName> in all areas.</p>
					<p>Many Czech estates, whose owners at the establishment of the <placeName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/terezin-places-place-iti-64">Protectorate</placeName> stayed abroad and did not return home, and estates which, at the demarcation, were located partly in the
							<placeName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/terezin-places-place-iti-64">Protectorate</placeName> and partly in the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/maps/wikipedia_52.5167_13.4.html">German Empire</placeName>, are placed under <term
							ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-600" type="subject">German administration</term>. It is expected, that similar extensions will take place in regard to <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2921044/federal-republic-of-germany.html"
							>German</placeName> Colonization. <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-889" type="subject">Jewish businesses</term> are mostly <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-930" type="subject">being handed over</term> to Germans.
						In <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-930" type="subject">Banks</term> and Industrial Enterprises, there is strong pressure from the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2921044/federal-republic-of-germany.html">German</placeName> side for
						mergers and transactions, so that the main influence of the company in question can be transferred to rich <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2921044/federal-republic-of-germany.html">German</placeName> banks.</p>
					<p>Perhaps some of these transactions - as a bank director familiar with Czech transactions in the post-World Bank banking sector, has told me - are merely restitutions, but in my opinion, the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2921044/federal-republic-of-germany.html"
							>German</placeName> proceed with greater severity and consistency than the <placeName ref="#ehri_dr_nationalities_czechs">Czechs</placeName> in this regard.</p>
					<p>Your honour</p>
					<p>Mr Chamberlain <persName ref="#ehri_dr_zahle_herluf">Herluf Zahle</persName></p>
					<p>Royal envoy in <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2950159/berlin.html">Berlin</placeName></p>
					<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19391109_03.jpg" n="3"/>
					<p>Everywhere the German language is being preferred over the Czech language. <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-1133" type="subject">Learning institutions</term> and <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-695" type="subject"
							>theatres</term> are taken over by the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/maps/wikipedia_52.5167_13.4.html">German Reich</placeName> and Germans are hired in all institutions and <ref
							target="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/terezin-jewishcouncil-organisation-jmp-392">administration offices</ref>. For example, an order has been imposed on the Tram conductors to call out the stations, first in German and then secondly in Czech, has caused
						unnecessary <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-813" type="subject">commotion</term> of the public.</p>
					<p>In <placeName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/terezin-places-place-iti-64">Bohemia and Moravia</placeName>, there were no <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-833" type="subject">food</term> shortages and before the war broke out, there
						were large supplies and industrial goods of great quality. In a short period of time, the stocks have been emptied and a <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-834" type="subject">rationing system</term> has been introduced. The rationing is not yet as
						widespread as in the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/maps/wikipedia_52.5167_13.4.html">German Reich</placeName> but it is just a matter of time before this happens and then there will be a "<term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-1175"
							type="subject">Gleichschaltung</term>". In addition, Dualism in the Administration contributes to the fact that the demand for rationed consumer goods is hardly as well organized as in the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/maps/wikipedia_52.5167_13.4.html">German
							Empire</placeName>. People often go to buy items, which according to the card system should be available just to find out that it is not.</p>
					<p>After the <term ref="#ehri_dr_Munich_Agreement" type="subject">Munich Decree</term> last year, the diminished territory of <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/8505031/czechoslovakia.html">Czechoslovakia</placeName> was established, and many <placeName
							ref="#ehri_dr_nationalities_czechs">Czechs</placeName>
						<term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-813" type="subject">believed</term> that with a little goodwill they could establish great relations with the German Empire. After the creation of the <placeName
							ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/terezin-places-place-iti-64">Protectorate</placeName>, a few people still hoped this was possible but now you won’t find a single Czech person that doesn’t feel resentment against Germany. I don’t think that these feelings will
						cause any outbreaks as long as the German discipline stands firm. The people are not armed and they know that the <orgName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_cb-438">German troops</orgName> and the <term
							ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-1119" type="subject">German police</term> will <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-601" type="subject">suppress</term> any demonstration with extreme brutality.</p>
					<p>In the first period of the <placeName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/terezin-places-place-iti-64">Protectorate</placeName> there where <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-598" type="subject">arrests</term> among the supporters of
							<persName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_pers-000030">Beneš'</persName>, undesired politicians, legionaries, and others. However, many of the arrested <pb facs="EHRI-DR-19391109_04.jpg" n="4"/> have since been <term
							ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-619" type="subject">released</term> and they believed that the main clash with Germans and people not well regarded by them had taken place. When the war broke out, <orgName
							ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_cb-350">Gestapo's</orgName> activity increased and in addition to the before-mentioned, a large number of members of the Military were now also arrested, as well as people from the industries, clerics and many others.
						Ever since it looks like the arrests won’t stop and it is difficult to see a system in the actions of <orgName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_cb-350">Gestapo</orgName>, you might see this as taking <term
							ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-663" type="subject">hostages</term>. A former Czech <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-1002" type="subject">politician</term> and <term
							ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-1007" type="subject">diplomat</term>, which has been retired for several years, told me about some of the arrests. He told about how certain people on the <orgName
							ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_cb-350">Gestapo's</orgName> list of arrests had remained in Freedom – at least until now – just because they were not at home when the <orgName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_cb-350"
							>Gestapo</orgName> came for them, so the police went on to the next one on the list. My informant told me that he changed his residence because he was afraid that he was going to be arrested. Many of the arrested people will be sent to the <placeName
							ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_camps-43" type="camp">concentration camp Buchenwald</placeName> in <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/maps/wikipedia_52.5167_13.4.html">Germany</placeName>. A reliable source told me that the internees are treated
						just as it is described in the newly published English <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-1068" type="subject">white paper</term> about German <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-496" type="subject">concentration
							camps</term>.</p>
					<p>The prominent <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-864" type="subject">Jews</term>, the ones who lived there before the World War, are not as affected by the <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-642" type="subject">Jewish
							persecutions</term> as others. I know of several examples of <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-891" type="subject">Jewish Bank</term> Directors, although retired, that are working a couple of hours daily in the Bank to explain the conditions to
						the new Managers and live peacefully in their villas. However, they had to turn in their cars and radios. I have also heard of <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-899" type="subject">Jewish lawyers</term> that work from home and then have their Aryan
						colleagues take the cases to court. Some <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-1427" type="subject">Jewish doctors</term> have been given temporary work in hospitals. <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-864" type="subject"
							>Jews</term> who can’t <pb facs="EHRI-DR-19391109_05.jpg" n="5"/> prove a permanent residence in the <placeName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/terezin-places-place-iti-64">Protectorate</placeName> seem to be facing very bad times. They will probably all be
							<term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-518" type="subject">transferred</term> to <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/798544/republic-of-poland.html">Poland</placeName>, to the regions around <placeName
							ref="http://www.geonames.org/702550/lviv.html">Lemberg</placeName>. From <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/3070328/moravska-ostrava.html">Mährisch Ostrau</placeName>, many Hundreds of <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-864" type="subject"
							>Jews</term> have already been sent to this area to do <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-556" type="subject">Labour service</term> in preparation for the great relocation.</p>
					<p>Under the conditions described above, the former Czechoslovakia National Day, on October 28, was met with great anxiety. When it was reported that the <placeName ref="#ehri_dr_nationalities_czechs">Czechs</placeName> wanted to grieve that day, the Germans had planned a
						mourning ceremony for the fallen people in Poland. The <placeName ref="#ehri_dr_nationalities_czechs">Czechs</placeName> then canceled their plans, and the Czech national unity party ordered its members to stay indoors and keep calm. The Germans also distanced themselves from
						holding the mourning ceremony. Despite the fact that it was <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-752" type="subject">Labour Day</term>, the traffic in the main streets was very busy. In spite of the <term
							ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-952" type="subject">prohibition</term>, many Czech people wore cockades with silk ribbons in the Czechoslovakia colours, and many male persons covered their heads with the same kind of cap of as the late President
							<persName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_pers-000266">Masaryk</persName> usually wore. All the <orgName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_cb-004772">Czech Police</orgName> was stationed in the Main Streets and the <orgName
							ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_cb-004312">German Police</orgName> and <orgName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_cb-429">S.S.</orgName>-members had taken up positions as a reserve in side streets and passages. The tensions erupted
						into fights as large sections the <orgName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_cb-358">S.A.</orgName>-members passed through the main streets with music, and various clashes between the Czech people's groups and the police took place. In some streets, the
							<term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-1000" type="subject">Communists</term> demonstrated, and German police had to support the Czech police to get the streets cleared. During the <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-255"
							type="subject">clashes</term>, a couple of persons (allegedly a dozen people) were killed and some of them were injured. A couple of young people were arrested.</p>
					<p/>
					<p>However, in view of the population’s agitated state of mind, the events must be considered less serious than one might have expected. This was also stated to me by a German Official from the <persName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_pers-000185"
							>Chancellor's</persName> Office. However, we cannot exclude that the incidents will give rise to new <pb facs="EHRI-DR-19391109_06.jpg" n="6"/>
						<term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-601" type="subject">reprisals</term> against the <placeName ref="#ehri_dr_nationalities_czechs">Czechs</placeName>, and the resentment against the Germans will then be further increased.</p>
					<p/>
					<p>Yours sincerely</p>
					<p>Your devoted</p>
					<p>(sign.) <persName ref="#ehri_dr_leth_eigil">Leth, Eigil</persName>.</p>
					<p>P.S.</p>
					<p>This Report was sent with a <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2661886/kingdom-of-sweden.html">Swedish</placeName> Courier to the Swedish Embassy in <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2950159/berlin.html">Berlin</placeName> for its Further Action.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
