<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://gitlab.inria.fr/dh-projects/workflow-ehri/-/raw/main/ODD/out/ODD-EHRI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="EHRI-DR-19430604-IT_EN" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title xml:lang="en">Dino Alfieri on the Situation in the General Government in 1943</title>
				<principal><affiliation><orgName>European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</orgName></affiliation></principal>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>
					<ref target="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</ref>
				</authority>
				<availability>
					<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title ref="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">EHRI Edition of Diplomatic Reports</title>
			</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/countries/it">Italy</country>
						<repository ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/institutions/it-002863">Archivio Storico Diplomatico del Ministero degli
							Affari Esteri</repository>
					</msIdentifier>
					<physDesc/>
				</msDesc>
				<bibl>Archivio Storico Diplomatico del Ministero degli Affari Esteri, Affari Politici 1923-1945, Polonia, busta 18. <textLang
						mainLang="en">Original in Italian.</textLang></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation>
				<date when="1943-06-04">4.6.1943</date>
				<placeName ref="#berlin">Berlin</placeName>
				<persName ref="#ehri_dr_alfieri_dino">Alfieri, Dino</persName>
				<idno>EHRI-DR-19430604-IT</idno>
			</creation>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="transcription">
				<!--<p>EHRI-DR-19430604-IT_EN</p>      
      <p>Report of the Ambassador in <placeName ref="#berlin"
        >Berlin</placeName>, <persName ref="#ehri_dr_alfieri_dino">Dino Alfieri</persName>, to the <orgName
          ref="#g005042">Foreign
        Ministry</orgName>, <date when="1943-06-04">4.6.1943</date></p>   
      <p>Cable No. 8466/1429</p>-->
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19430604-IT_01.jpg" n="1"/>
				<p>R. Embassy of <placeName ref="#italian-republic">Italy</placeName></p>
				<p>Addressed to R. <orgName ref="#g005042"> Ministry of Foreign Affairs</orgName></p>
				<p>Very confidential</p>
				<p>[Handwritten initials in red pencil:] M [<persName ref="#p000287">Mussolini</persName>] V [visto = seen]</p>
				<p>Berlin, <date when="1943-06-04">4th June 1943</date></p>
				<p>Re: Situation in the <term ref="#t1191" type="subject">General Governorate</term></p>
				<p>Ref.: My Cable No. 8190/1374 of 28th May last</p>
				<p>The Inspector of the <term ref="#t964" type="subject">Fasci</term> in <placeName ref="#federal-republic-of-germany"
						>Germany</placeName>, who has returned from a brief visit to <placeName ref="#warsaw">Warsaw</placeName>, has sent me the
					following report on the situation in the <term ref="#t1191" type="subject">Generalgouvernement</term> General Governorate:</p>
				<p>“After the latest <term ref="#t604" type="subject">air-raids</term> by the <term ref="#t1000" type="subject">Bolsheviks</term>, the
					town appears very much <term ref="#t356" type="subject">damaged</term>. It is estimated that the <orgName ref="#g404">German
						bombings</orgName>, when Warsaw was conquered, damaged 15-20% of the buildings, and the damage inflicted by the Bolsheviks is
					estimated to be the same. This means that 30-40% of the buildings are almost totally destroyed, every couple of hundred meters one
					comes upon large open spaces covered with rubble. […]</p>
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19430604-IT_02.jpg" n="2"/>
				<p>In the <term ref="#t545" type="subject">ghetto</term>, a vast area right in the <placeName ref="#l1106" type="ghetto">centre of
						town</placeName> and <term ref="#t552" type="subject">separated</term> from it only by a high wall built for this purpose,
					when <term ref="#t1032" type="subject">German authorities</term> requested that a few thousand <term ref="#t864" type="subject"
						>Jews</term> should be sent out to <term ref="#t556" type="subject">work</term> in factories, the Jews refused to obey the
						<term ref="#t201" type="subject">order</term>, saying that they had not heard again from the Jews that had previously <term
						ref="#t551" type="subject">left the ghetto</term>, As we know, <term ref="#t254" type="subject">a war</term> ensued that is
					still continuing. On the one side <term ref="#t872" type="subject">the Jews</term>, of whom there are still perhaps about 15,000
					and who have dug themselves in inside the ghetto, building underground bunkers up to thirty meters deep, <term ref="#t1095"
						type="subject">powerfully armoured</term> and equipped with heavy and light machine guns, who are supported and led by <term
						ref="#t240" type="subject">Bolsheviks</term> sent from <placeName ref="#moscow">Moscow</placeName>, and have huge stockpiles
					of food and ammunition that could last them for years of fighting. On the other, <orgName ref="#g437">SS</orgName> units who
					systematically and without needlessly endangering the lives of their soldiers advance from house to house, following even the
					sewers and the underground canals where fighting goes on, and subdue <term ref="#t246" type="subject">resistance</term>. The
						<orgName ref="#g350">Gestapo</orgName> Chief told me that he expects to <term ref="#t255" type="subject">subdue all
						resistance</term> within a few weeks.</p>
				<p>In this climate, while the population is being bombarded from the sky, mined underground by the <term ref="#t1081" type="subject"
						>fighting</term> within the ghetto and by the ghetto’s <term ref="#t1215" type="subject">emissaries</term> (<term ref="#t1009"
						type="subject">Communists</term> and Jews who have managed to leave the ghetto and are hiding in town) and forced on the
					ground to rely on the <term ref="#t1051" type="subject">black market</term> to survive among all kinds of threats, <term
						ref="#t240" type="subject">secret organizations</term> of Communists and Jews flourish, as well as others by Polish
					nationalists, both of which try to prepare the revolt and for the time being want to cause terror among the ruling group.</p>
				<p>The organizers warn the <term ref="#t1032" type="subject">German rulers</term> and those <placeName ref="#republic-of-poland"
						>Poles</placeName> that are believed to <term ref="#t223" type="subject">sympathize</term> with them that they will be <term
						ref="#t541" type="subject">liquidated</term>, and every day <pb facs="EHRI-DR-19430604-IT_03.jpg" n="3"/> there are murders
					taking place in circumstances worthy of a crime thriller. I have seen Gestapo chiefs and <orgName ref="#g407">Nazi party</orgName>
					leaders, always in civilian clothes, going around with their revolver at the ready. I have noticed that when they have to go
					somewhere, they resort to stratagems to mislead those who might be following them. […]</p>
				<p>During my stay in Warsaw I have contacted local leaders of the General Governorate, of the Nazi party, of the Gestapo, of Russian
					and Polish circles close to the <term ref="#t1032" type="subject">German occupying authorities</term>. […]</p>
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19430604-IT_04.jpg" n="4"/>
				<p>These same people suggest that a solution might be found by transforming the struggle, which right now has taken on the character
					of an exclusively German struggle against <placeName ref="#russian-federation">Russia</placeName>, thus endowing <persName
						ref="#p000463">Stalin</persName> with a pedestal as Russia’s <term ref="#t1065" type="subject">saviour</term>, and having it
					revert, as the <persName ref="#p000287">Duce</persName> had suggested, to its true essence: the struggle of Europe, led by the
						<term ref="#t1027" type="subject">Axis</term>, against Bolshevism.</p>
				<p>For this struggle one could rely on the organization of some millions of Russians who would fight even more fanatically than <term
						ref="#t1027" type="subject">Axis</term> troops against the <term ref="#t240" type="subject">Bolsheviks</term> to free their
					fatherland from <term ref="#t240" type="subject">Bolshevism</term>. To this <placeName ref="#russian-federation"
						>Russia</placeName> military organization, the armed forces of the <term ref="#t1027" type="subject">Axis</term> ought to
					provide the structure and, most importantly, the reserves.</p>
				<p>To make the military struggle of the <term ref="#t1027" type="subject">Axis</term> against <term ref="#t240" type="subject"
						>Bolshevism</term> feasible in this manner one would have to establish, as a fundamental prerequisite, the <term
						ref="#t1021?dlid=deu" type="subject">political conditions</term> for the cooperation of all anti-Bolshevik Polish and
						<placeName ref="#russian-federation">Russia</placeName> peoples on a political platform that might look like this: Russia to
					the <placeName ref="#russian-federation">Russia</placeName> – <placeName ref="#republic-of-poland">Poland</placeName> to the
					Poles, both obviously under the <term ref="#t597" type="subject">control</term> of the <term ref="#t1027" type="subject"
						>Axis</term> powers and their allies; <term ref="#t1080" type="subject">war</term> against <term ref="#t240" type="subject"
						>Bolshevism</term>; <term ref="#t536" type="subject">war against Jews</term>; recognition of private <term ref="#t945"
						type="subject">property</term>; a controlled freedom of <term ref="#t933" type="subject">trade</term>.”</p>
				<p>The Royal Ambassador</p>
				<p><persName ref="#ehri_dr_alfieri_dino">Alfieri</persName>
				</p>
				<p> </p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
