<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://gitlab.inria.fr/dh-projects/workflow-ehri/-/raw/main/ODD/out/ODD-EHRI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="EHRI-DR-19430601-IT_EN" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title xml:lang="en">Maurilio Coppini on the “Jewish question and Romanian approach” in 1943</title>
				<principal><affiliation><orgName>European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</orgName></affiliation></principal>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>
					<ref target="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</ref>
				</authority>
				<availability>
					<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title ref="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">EHRI Edition of Diplomatic Reports</title>
			</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/countries/it">Italy </country>
						<repository ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/institutions/it-002863">Archivio Storico Diplomatico del Ministero degli
							Affari Esteri</repository>
					</msIdentifier>
					<physDesc/>
				</msDesc>
				<bibl>Archivio Storico Diplomatico del Ministero degli Affari Esteri, AG Uff IV. Posizione S.E. 27.869, busta R, fasc. Romania.
						<textLang mainLang="en">Original in Italian.</textLang></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation>
				<date when="1943-06-01">1.6.1943</date>
				<placeName ref="#odessa">Odessa</placeName>
				<persName ref="#ehri_dr_coppini_maurilio">Coppini, Maurilio</persName>
				<idno>EHRI-DR-19430601-IT</idno>
			</creation>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="transcription">
				<!--<p>EHRI-DR-19430601-IT_EN</p>
      <p>Report by the Consul General of Odessa, Maurilio Coppini, for the Ministry of Foreign
        Affairs, <date when="1943-06-01">1.6.1943</date>.</p>
      <p>R. Consulate General of Italy</p>
      <p>No. 765/184</p>
      <p>Secret</p>
      <p>Odessa, <date when="1943-06-01">1st June 1943</date> – XXI</p>
      <p>R. Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Rome</p>
      <p>and cc R. Legation of Italy, Bucharest</p>-->
				<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19430601-IT_01.jpg" n="1"/>
				<p><term ref="#t351" type="subject">Jewish question</term> and <placeName ref="#romania">Romanian</placeName> approach.</p>
				<p>My report no. 649/137 of <date when="1943-05-08">8.5.1943</date>.</p>
				<p><persName ref="#ehri_dr_cassulo_andrea">Nuncio Cassulo’s</persName> visit to <placeName ref="#transnistria"
						>Transnistria</placeName> apparently had a far more definite purpose than had been assumed. I have heard, that is, that the
					Holy Father is said to have expressed the wish to exert a direct influence on the <placeName ref="#romania">Romanian</placeName>
					<term ref="#t948" type="subject">Government</term> so as to obtain a more humane treatment of <term ref="#t864" type="subject"
						>Jews</term>. Monsignor Cassulo’s journey to <placeName ref="#transnistria">Transnistria</placeName> is believed therefore to
					have been a voyage of inspection in order to report to the Vatican on the matter. As to the question if the Nuncio’s journey
					served indeed the purpose of providing an exact picture of the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jewish</term> situation in
						<placeName ref="#transnistria">Transnistria</placeName>, I already reported on this in the above-mentioned report. As far as I
					know, on the contrary, the Nuncio was not convinced by the <q>tame</q>
					<term ref="#t545" type="subject">ghetto</term> he was shown.</p>
				<p>Reportedly, the pressure from the Vatican concerning the treatment of <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> was joined by
					further pressure from the international <term ref="#g3754" type="subject">Red Cross</term>, which has friends and supporters among
					the highest Romanian circles.</p>
				<p>As for <placeName ref="#transnistria">Transnistria</placeName>, the situation is as follows.</p>
				<p>When <placeName ref="#romania">Romanian</placeName> and <term ref="#t1152" type="subject">German</term>
					<term ref="#t1076" type="subject">troops</term>
					<term ref="#t632" type="subject">occupied</term>
					<placeName ref="#transnistria">Transnistria</placeName>, the situation of <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> at first
					experienced ups and downs. During the first days – particularly in <placeName ref="#odessa">Odessa</placeName> where there were
					about a hundred thousand persons who had not been <term ref="#t623" type="subject">evacuated</term> – <placeName ref="#romania"
						>Romanian</placeName> authorities carried out a <term ref="#t647" type="subject">registration</term> and some <term
						ref="#t598" type="subject">arrests</term>. After the terrorist acts and particularly after the one of 23rd October there were
						<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19430601-IT_02.jpg" n="2"/> brutal reprisals. It is not easy to give numbers, but many thousands, perhaps
					tens of thousands of <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> were <term ref="#t532" type="subject">eliminated</term> and
						<term ref="#t598" type="subject">arrested</term>. In was then that temporary <term ref="#t545" type="subject">ghettoes</term>
					and places for <term ref="#t614" type="subject">concentration</term> were created. Orders however were as yet unclear, and already
					in November many of these <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> were set free. It was only in December ’41 and in January
					’42, during the harshest of winters, that <placeName ref="#romania">Romanian</placeName> authorities decided to <term ref="#t518"
						type="subject">remove</term> the Jews from <placeName ref="#odessa">Odessa</placeName>. I hardly need to describe how this
						<term ref="#t203" type="subject">emigration</term> took place. The <term ref="#t1152" type="subject">Germans</term> themselves
					admit that it might have been carried out with greater humanity. Anyway, those who managed to reach on foot the places of <term
						ref="#t614" type="subject">concentration</term>, were banned to <term ref="#t545" type="subject">ghettoes</term>, that is to
					sites in the suburbs of small provincial towns. Considering the meteorological and political climate, they were treated with scant
					regard and no doubt the well-known <term ref="#t542" type="subject">oppressive measures</term> will have continued there, set off
					by local authorities. The <term ref="#t1152" type="subject">Germans</term>, for their part, have acted similarly in the areas
					surrounding the territories inhabited by <term ref="#t1152" type="subject">German</term> communities.</p>
				<p>This system of things, which by the way has been useful to all to rebuild what had been destroyed, to make up for losses and to
					create benefits, lasted more or less intensely, more or less arbitrarily until June of last year. After that the situation
					stabilized or, to put it more exactly, was rendered legal. For a start, <term ref="#t542" type="subject">rules</term> began to be
					published regarding the place of residence of <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term>, the deadline for reporting to the
						<term ref="#t545" type="subject">ghetto</term>, also the activity of <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> inside and
					outside the <term ref="#t545" type="subject">ghettoes</term> has been specified, they have been granted a form of <term ref="#t2"
						type="subject">self-government</term>, and so forth. It is hard to say if the <term ref="#t542" type="subject">oppressive
						measures</term> have ceased. A great deal would depend on the local authorities and on whether the <term ref="#t864"
						type="subject">Jews</term> are able to reach a compromise with them. What can be said with certainty is that, as far as I
					know, during the past months the situation of <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> has not grown any worse.</p>
				<p>I wanted to ascertain this in person. In <placeName ref="#balta">Balta</placeName>, for instance, there are approx. fifteen
					thousand <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> arrived from <placeName ref="#romania">Romania</placeName>.</p>
				<p>The <term ref="#t545" type="subject">ghetto</term> is in a suburban part of the town and is made up of wretched cottages where a
					great many <term ref="#t819" type="subject">families</term> live in deplorable <term ref="#t295" type="subject">hygienic</term>
					conditions. There is a <term ref="#t666" type="subject">curfew</term> imposed on the <term ref="#t545" type="subject"
						>ghetto</term>
					<pb facs="EHRI-DR-19430601-IT_03.jpg" n="3"/> which starts at sundown. The <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> are not
					allowed into the public market, nor can they frequent the <term ref="#t1071" type="subject">town’s establishments</term>. There is
					a municipal authority that manages the community and supplies the required manpower. Jews are employed in <ref
						target="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/terezin-jewishcouncil-organisation-jmp-41">public works</ref> in the towns and
					in the surrounding areas. Those who <term ref="#t943" type="subject">work</term> receive one mark a day and a substantial bread
					ration.</p>
				<p>The more unfortunate <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term>, however, live or rather vegetate inside the <term ref="#t545"
						type="subject">ghetto</term>; the more able ones and particularly the young female elements manage to find ways to live
					outside the <term ref="#t545" type="subject">ghetto</term> and in any case enjoy visible advantages for their lives.</p>
				<p>It seems that this situation in <placeName ref="#balta">Balta</placeName> and also in <placeName ref="#ribnita"
						>Rybnitsa</placeName> is more or less identical to that of the other <term ref="#t545" type="subject">ghettoes</term> in
						<placeName ref="#transnistria">Transnistria</placeName>, where the numbers of <term ref="#t518" type="subject">deported</term>
					or <term ref="#t614" type="subject">concentrated Jews</term> change all the time. (I have myself seen in <placeName ref="#balta"
						>Balta</placeName> about a thousand <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> just arrived from <placeName ref="#romania"
						>Romania</placeName>, mostly young people assigned to four months of compulsory work there). In Bereswka a certain number of
						<term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> has even been assigned to the Prefecture, to posts of varying importance, with
					regular salaries.</p>
				<p>This denotes a marked improvement compared to last year. The fact in itself would not have any great significance, if some recent
					information, such as the news that has prompted the present report, did not confer on the situation an aspect that I believe ought
					to be pointed out. I have been informed by an excellent source that recently, at an ordinary conference of the Prefects of
						<placeName ref="#transnistria">Transnistria</placeName> held by the Governor in <placeName ref="#ribnita"
					>Rybniysa</placeName>, these officials allegedly gave as their opinion that in the present situation, as long as the fate of the
						<term ref="#t1080" type="subject">war</term> remains uncertain at the very least, it seemed advisable to improve the treatment
					of <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> or to lessen the <term ref="#t658" type="subject">restrictions</term> on their
					freedom and allow them ways to resume a greater activity.</p>
				<p>Reportedly there was even talk of giving the Jews some <term ref="#t1042" type="subject">compensation</term> for the damages they
					have suffered. Thus their situation would be rendered equal to that of the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> in
						<placeName ref="#bucharest">Bucharest</placeName> and in other <placeName ref="#romania">Romanian</placeName> towns.</p>
				<p>Naturally this <term ref="#t752" type="subject">news</term>, which is confirmed <pb facs="EHRI-DR-19430601-IT-04.jpg" n="4"/> by
					the discernible general trend towards improving the <term ref="#t831" type="subject">condition</term> of <term ref="#t864"
						type="subject">Jews</term>, has annoyed <term ref="#t1152" type="subject">German</term> circles and made them mistrustful.
					They suggest that the <term ref="#t351" type="subject">Jewish question</term> cannot be handled in <placeName ref="#transnistria"
						>Transnistria</placeName> any differently from how it has been handled until now. The reasons given by the Prefects and by
					those in favour of improving the treatment of <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> arise from a pessimistic view of the
						<term ref="#t1027" type="subject">Axis</term>’s general situation, and that is totally unacceptable. They are therefore
					inclined to believe that this entire matter is essentially decided by the <term ref="#t948" type="subject">Government</term> in
						<placeName ref="#bucharest">Bucharest</placeName>, which is influenced by the steps undertaken by the Vatican and by <term
						ref="#l415" type="subject">Geneva</term>, and has easily taken root in the Anglophile and Francophile circles, whether <term
						ref="#t1076" type="subject">military</term> or civilian, of <placeName ref="#romania">Romania</placeName>. The <term
						ref="#t351" type="subject">Jewish question</term> in <placeName ref="#transnistria">Transnistria</placeName> is therefore
					believed to be an indication of the general situation in Romania and of the opinion held by certain classes of <placeName
						ref="#romania">Romanians</placeName> concerning the development of that situation.</p>
				<p>Obviously, I am reporting all this because it is in accordance with ascertained facts and conversations that have actually taken
					place. There can be no doubt, in any case, that in local <placeName ref="#romania">Romanian</placeName> circles there is a
					widespread feeling that the present events warrant serious worries, a feeling caused mainly by the uncertainty about <term
						ref="#t1152" type="subject">German</term> intentions and capabilities with regard to <placeName ref="#russian-federation"
						>Russia</placeName>.</p>
				<p><persName ref="#ehri_dr_coppini_maurilio">Coppini</persName></p>
				<p> </p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
