<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?teipublisher template="document.html"?>
<?xml-model href="../../Guidelines/out/Documentation-Correspondance.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="EHRI-ET-ZIH3010481_EN" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en">Ela Rozenberg, experiences in the Treblinka extermination camp</title>
                <title xml:lang="fr">Ela Rozenberg, expériences dans le camp d'extermination de Treblinka</title>
                <principal><affiliation><orgName>European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</orgName></affiliation></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <orgName>EHRI Edition of Early Holocaust Testimony</orgName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <persName>Michał Czajka</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <persName>Marta Wojas</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <persName>Dagmara Chełstowska</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <ref target="https://www.ehri-project.eu">European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</ref>
                </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0">Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title type="main">EHRI Edition of Early Holocaust Testimonies</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <location>
                            <address>
                                <street>Tłomackie 3/5</street>
                                <postCode>00-090 </postCode>
                                <settlement>Warsaw</settlement>
                                <country ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/countries/pl">Poland</country>
                            </address>
                        </location>
                        <repository ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/institutions/pl-003146">Jewish Historical Institute in Warsaw</repository>
                        <collection ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/units/pl-003146-301#desc-pol">Holocaust Survivor Testimonies (coll.
                            301)</collection>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc/>
                </msDesc>
                <bibl>Jewish Historical Institute in Warsaw, Holocaust Survivor Testimonies (coll. 301), Ela Rozenberg Testimony (301/481). <textLang
                        mainLang="pl">Original in Polish.</textLang></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="fr">L'encodage de ce document s'est fait dans le cadre du projet 'EHRI Edition of Early Holocaust Testimonies'</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The encoding of this document is part of the project 'EHRI Edition of Early Holocaust Testimonies'</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation><date when="1945">1945</date>, <persName ref="#ehri_et_rozenberg_ela">Ela Rozenberg</persName>, <placeName ref="#warsaw"
                    >Warsaw</placeName>, <placeName ref="#l2032" type="camp">Treblinka</placeName>, <term ref="#t498" type="subject">death
                    camps</term>, <term ref="#t529" type="subject">extermination</term>, <term ref="#t499" type="subject">gas chambers</term>, <term
                    ref="#t516" type="subject">corpse burning</term>
                <idno>EHRI-ET-ZIH3010481</idno></creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>testimony</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">Polish</language>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <abstract>
                <p>Testimony of Ela Rozenberg on the deportations of Jews from the Warsaw Ghetto and the transport to the Treblinka extermination
                    camp. After the selection, she was assigned to sort the clothes of the murdered Jews and to bury their bodies.</p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when-iso="2022-07-21" who="#floriane.chiffoleau">Added the original version of the testimony</change>
            <change when-iso="2021-11-05" who="#floriane.chiffoleau">Upgrading TEI encoding</change>
            <change when-iso="2021-10-29" who="#floriane.chiffoleau">Upgrading TEI encoding</change>
            <change when-iso="2020" who="#ehri">Encoding of the file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="original">
                <p>Relacja <persName ref="#ehri_et_rozenberg_ela" type="ehri">Eli Rosenberga</persName> (sygn. 301/481)</p>
                <p>Oryginał, rękopis, 2 strony, 235 x 340 mm, język polski</p>
                <p><pb facs="EHRI-ET-ZIH3010481_01.jpg" n="1"/> Ja, <persName ref="#ehri_et_rozenberg_ela" type="ehri">Ela Rosenberg</persName>,
                    urodzony <date when="1942">1924</date> roku w <placeName ref="#warsaw" type="ehri">Warszawie,</placeName> przy <placeName
                        ref="#warsaw" type="ehri">ulicy Gęsia 25</placeName>. <term ref="#t822" type="subject">Ojciec</term> mój został <term
                        ref="#t532" type="subject">zamordowany</term> przez <term ref="#t1159" type="subject">Niemców</term>
                    <date when="1940">1940</date> roku. W <date when="1942-08">sierpniu 1942</date> roku zostałem wywieziony z <term ref="#t545"
                        type="subject">ghetta</term> wraz z <term ref="#t822" type="subject">rodziną</term> do <placeName ref="#l2032" type="camp"
                        >Treblinki</placeName>, wpakując nas po 100 osób w <term ref="#t522" type="subject">wagon</term>. Gdy <term ref="#t522"
                        type="subject">szałon</term><note type="gloss" xml:lang="yid">Eszelon (pociąg).</note> zatrzymał się było już świt, widziałem
                    przez zakratowane okienko dworzec <placeName ref="#malkinia-gorna" type="ehri">Małkinia</placeName>, w tej chwili <term
                        ref="#t1159" type="subject">niemcy</term> zaczęli odłączać po 15 <term ref="#t940" type="subject">wagonów</term>, wjeżdżając
                    przez specjalną bocznicę, prowadzącą do <term ref="#t498" type="subject">obozu</term>, w chwili, gdy <term ref="#t522"
                        type="subject">wagony</term> zatrzymali się, rozpoczęli się krzyki: <foreign xml:lang="de">raus, raus</foreign>. <term
                        ref="#t825" type="subject">Kobiety</term> osobno, <term ref="#t826" type="subject">mężczyźni</term> osobno, pożegnając się z
                        <term ref="#t822" type="subject">matką</term> i <term ref="#t822" type="subject">siostrami</term> udałem się w stronę <term
                        ref="#t826" type="subject">mężczyzn</term>, tam <term ref="#t1159" type="subject">niemcy</term>
                    <term ref="#t555" type="subject">kazali nam siadać na ziemi</term>, mówiąc do nas że tu są kąpiele, i gdy wykąpiemy się, wtedy
                    każdy połączy się spowrotem z <term ref="#t822" type="subject">rodziną</term>, dostanie nowe <term ref="#t836" type="subject"
                        >ubrania</term> i pojedziemy dalej na <term ref="#t943" type="subject">robotę</term>. W tej chwili przybiegł <term
                        ref="#t1159" type="subject">niemiec</term> do nas siedzących na ziemi, wybierając 30 chłopców i mnie, mówiąc, że idziemy do
                        <term ref="#t556" type="subject">roboty</term>, ciesząc się, że się znowu zobaczę z <term ref="#t822" type="subject"
                        >matką</term> i <term ref="#t822" type="subject">siostrami</term>, zaprowadził nas na dużym <term ref="#t944" type="subject"
                        >placu</term>, na którym znajdowało się ogromne stosy <term ref="#t836" type="subject">ubrań</term>, waliz, buty męskie,
                    damskie, tomołoki, <term ref="#t660" type="subject">pieniądze</term> i jeszcze stosy różnych rzeczy, wtedy <term ref="#t1159"
                        type="subject">niemiec</term> kazał rzucić z siebie <term ref="#t836" type="subject">palta</term> i wziąść się do <term
                        ref="#t943" type="subject">roboty</term>, robota ta polegała na <term ref="#t411" type="subject">sortowanie</term> każdej
                    rzeczy: buty do butów, <term ref="#t836" type="subject">palta</term> do <term ref="#t836" type="subject">palt</term> itd. Nie
                    wiedząc o niczym co tu się dzieje, pytałem się kilku chłopców, no nikt mnie nie dał rzeciwistej odpowiedzi, dowiedziałem się
                    tylko, że <term ref="#t658" type="subject">nie wolno rozmawiać</term> między sobą. Wtem zauważyłem znajomego człowieka, który
                    mieszkał ze mną razem w jednym podwórku, on był wywieziony o 4 dni przedtem niż ja, więc zapytawszy go, co tu jest i gdzie wszyscy
                        <term ref="#t826" type="subject">mężczyźni</term> i <term ref="#t825" type="subject">kobiety</term> są, wykręcił się i z
                    zapłakanemi oczami odpowiedział mi jedno tylko słowo: już niemasz <term ref="#t822" type="subject">matkę</term> i <term
                        ref="#t822" type="subject">siostry</term>, nie zdążąc mnie poinformować jak i co z nimi zrobili, przybiegli do nas 2 <term
                        ref="#t1159" type="subject">niemcy</term> i zaczęli nas katować <term ref="#t564" type="subject">knutami</term> po głowie i na
                    dodatku po 25 knutów na gołe <term ref="#t555" type="subject">ciało</term>, z wielką trudnością podniosłem się i <term ref="#t411"
                        type="subject">sortując</term> jeszcze dwie godziny do godziny 10 wieczór, spędzali nas do <term ref="#t836" type="subject"
                        >baraków</term>, wtem zaczęły się krzyki po niemiecku: wsadzili nóż w <persName ref="#ehri_et_bialas_max" type="ehri"
                        >Maksa</persName>
                    <note type="gloss">SS‑Unterscharführer Max Bialas was killed on September 10 or 11, 1942 by Meir Berliner, a prisoner. As
                        retaliation, the Germans killed 160 prisoners.</note>, który przez parę godzin zdechł. Wtedy zaczęli <term ref="#t653"
                        type="subject">strzelać</term> na nas i <term ref="#t562" type="subject">katować</term> nas bezlitośnie, czem tylko mogli.
                    Tłoczyliśmy się jak barany, jeden na drugiego, wtedy padając na ziemię, dostałem <term ref="#t562" type="subject">cios</term>
                    bagnetem po palcach. Po tej godzinnej gonitwie, <term ref="#t540" type="subject">zabijając</term> 100 chłopców, zagnali nas do
                        <term ref="#t837" type="subject">baraków</term>, dopiero w <term ref="#t837" type="subject">baraku</term> zerwałem kawał z
                        <term ref="#t836" type="subject">koszuli</term> i zabandażowałem rękę. Każdy jeden z płaczem i <term ref="#t791"
                        type="subject">bólem</term> położył się na ziemi trochę odpocząć, a chłopcy, co już byli tam po kilka dni lub tygodni
                    wiedzieli już, że trzeba <term ref="#t486" type="subject">wstać</term>, gdy jeszcze szarawo jest na dworze i czekać, jak otworzą
                        <term ref="#t837" type="subject">barak</term>, ale tym razem baraku nie otworzyli, tylko grożąc nas karabinami i mówiąc, że
                    wszystkich zaraz <term ref="#t532" type="subject">zamordują,</term> więc czekając zniecierpliwością na <term ref="#t829"
                        type="subject">śmierć</term>, otworzyli <term ref="#t837" type="subject">barak</term> dopiero o 11 godzinie, rycząc alles
                    raus, ustawili nas w szeregach i <term ref="#t411" type="subject">odłącząc 200 chłopców</term>, <term ref="#t533" type="subject"
                        >rozstrzelając</term> ich karabinami maszynowymi, a resztę pognali do <term ref="#t943" type="subject">roboty</term>, <term
                        ref="#t653" type="subject">ukarając</term> ich na 3 dni bez <term ref="#t832" type="subject">jedzenia</term> i bez picia, po
                    południu przyszedł <term ref="#t1159" type="subject">niemiec</term> do grupy, co <term ref="#t411" type="subject">sortują</term>
                    buty, zabierając 50 chłopców wraz ze mną mówił nam, że idziem tylko na 10 minut do lekkiej <term ref="#t943" type="subject"
                        >roboty</term>, prowadząc nas przez cały plac do jakieś bramy, no gdy my przeszli tą bramę, krew we mnie zastygła, zauważyłem
                    stos <term ref="#t540" type="subject">ludzi</term>
                    <term ref="#t515" type="subject">martwych</term>, leżących na ziemi i podchodzących do nich zakrwawionych chłopców z nosiłkami,
                    łapiąc <term ref="#t515" type="subject">trupa</term> za ręce i nogi, położyli go na tragę i uciekają z nim. Domyślając się o tym
                    wszystkim, patrzałem na to z łzami w oczach, tu ni stąd ni zowąd otrzymałem uderzenie pajczą po głowę, chłopcy, którzy byli tu już
                    po kilku dni, powiedzieli nam, żeby po dwu chłopców wziąść tragę i nosić <term ref="#t515" type="subject">trupów</term> do jamy,
                    podskoczyłem z prędkością do nosiłek, biorąc tragę z partnerem udaliśmy się w stronę <term ref="#t499" type="subject">komór
                        gazowych</term>. Na drodze <pb facs="EHRI-ET-ZIH3010481_02.jpg" n="2"/> do kabin obdarzyli nas <term ref="#t564"
                        type="subject">knutami</term> wołając <q>prędzej wy psy</q>. Dobiegłem do rampy biegiem, postawiliśmy tragę na ziemi i kładąc
                        <term ref="#t515" type="subject">trupa</term> niezgrabnie na tragę, wtedy <term ref="#t1159" type="subject">Niemcy</term>
                    zaczęli nas bezlitośnie katować, mnie zwalili na ziemię i kopiąc mnie butem w głowę, krzycząc, że nie wziąłem prawidłowo <term
                        ref="#t515" type="subject">trupa</term> na tragę. Z trudnością podniosłem się z ziemi i biorąc <term ref="#t515"
                        type="subject">trupa</term> z kolegą uciekliśmy w stronę <term ref="#t539" type="subject">jamy</term>. W drogę do <term
                        ref="#t539" type="subject">jamy</term> biegali chłopcy z <term ref="#t515" type="subject">trupami</term>, jeden za drugim.
                    Zbliżając się do jamy, zobaczyłem nową tragiczną scenę, w <term ref="#t539" type="subject">jamach</term> widziałem tylko wielką
                    kałużę krwi i wrzucając <term ref="#t515" type="subject">trupów</term> do <term ref="#t539" type="subject">jamy</term> utonęli w
                    krwi. Miesiąc cały nosiłem <term ref="#t515" type="subject">trupów</term>, potem przenosili mnie na rampę, <term ref="#t558"
                        type="subject">praca</term> była bardzo ciężka, wyciągając <term ref="#t515" type="subject">trupów</term>
                    <term ref="#t534" type="subject">zagazowanych</term>. 5 miesiące wyciągałem <term ref="#t515" type="subject">trupów</term>. Tych
                    wszystkich <term ref="#t515" type="subject">trupów</term> rzucano do <term ref="#t539" type="subject">jam</term>, posypując ich
                    chlorkiem, w <date when="1943-02">1943</date> roku, w <date when="1943-02">II miesiącu</date> przyszedł rozkaz wszystkich <term
                        ref="#t515" type="subject">trupów</term> wykopać i <term ref="#t516" type="subject">spalić</term>, więc sprowadzono 3 <term
                        ref="#t557" type="subject">dźwigi</term>, które zanurzając się koszem do <term ref="#t539" type="subject">jamy</term> i
                    chwytąc zębami kawały mięsa i kości, wyrzucali na powierzchnię, stojące chłopcy z widłami kładli kawały mięsa i kości na nosiłki i
                    zaniesiono do ognia, <term ref="#t516" type="subject">spaląc</term> dziennie 8 tysięcy ludzi.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="transcription">
                <p><persName ref="#ehri_et_rozenberg_ela" type="ehri">Eli Rozenberg</persName> Testimony (doc. 301/481)</p>
                <p>Original, manuscript, 2 pages, 235 x 340 mm, Polish language</p>
                <p><pb facs="EHRI-ET-ZIH3010481_01.jpg" n="1"/> I, <persName ref="#ehri_et_rozenberg_ela" type="ehri">Eli Rozenberg</persName>, born
                    in <date when="1924">1924</date> in <placeName ref="#warsaw" type="ehri">Warsaw</placeName>, at <placeName ref="#warsaw"
                        type="ehri">25 Gęsia Street</placeName>. My father was <term ref="#t536" type="subject">murdered</term> by the <term
                        ref="#t1159" type="subject">Germans</term> in <date when="1940">1940</date>. In <date when="1942-08">August 1942</date>, I was
                        <term ref="#t115" type="subject">deported</term> from the <placeName ref="#l1106" type="ghetto">ghetto</placeName> to
                        <placeName ref="#l2032" type="camp">Treblinka</placeName> along with the rest of my family, we were packed 100 to a <term
                        ref="#t940" type="subject">wagon</term>. When the <term ref="#t522" type="subject">train</term> stopped, it was already dawn I
                    saw the <placeName ref="#malkinia-gorna" type="ehri">Małkinia</placeName> station through the little barred window, at that moment
                    the <term ref="#t1159" type="subject">Germans</term> started detaching groups of 15 <term ref="#t940" type="subject">wagons</term>
                    that went on a special side-track leading to the <term ref="#t498" type="subject">camp</term>, and when the <term ref="#t940"
                        type="subject">wagons</term> stopped, they started shouting <q><foreign xml:lang="de">raus, raus</foreign></q>. <term
                        ref="#t825" type="subject">Women</term> and <term ref="#t826" type="subject">men</term> were <term ref="#t411" type="subject"
                        >separate</term>, saying good-bye to my <term ref="#t822" type="subject">mother</term> and <term ref="#t822" type="subject"
                        >sisters</term>, I managed to get to the <term ref="#t826" type="subject">men’s</term> side, where the <term ref="#t1159"
                        type="subject">Germans</term> ordered us to <term ref="#t555" type="subject">sit on the ground</term>, telling us that the
                        <term ref="#t533" type="subject">baths</term> are here and that when we are bathed then everyone would be reunited with their
                    family, would get new <term ref="#t836" type="subject">clothing</term> and we would travel on further to where we would be <term
                        ref="#t943" type="subject">working</term>. At this point a <term ref="#t1159" type="subject">German</term> ran up to us as we
                    were <term ref="#t555" type="subject">sitting</term> on the ground, <term ref="#t411" type="subject">picking out</term> 30 boys
                    and me, telling us that we are going off to <term ref="#t943" type="subject">work</term>, happy that I would see my <term
                        ref="#t822" type="subject">mother</term> and <term ref="#t822" type="subject">sisters</term> again, we took us to a big <term
                        ref="#t944" type="subject">yard</term> where there were huge piles of <term ref="#t836" type="subject">clothing</term>,
                    suitcases, men’s and women’s shoes, baggage, <term ref="#t660" type="subject">money</term>, and mounds of other things, then the
                        <term ref="#t1159" type="subject">German</term> ordered us to take off our coats and start <term ref="#t943" type="subject"
                        >working</term>, the <term ref="#t943" type="subject">work</term> consisted of <term ref="#t411" type="subject">sorting</term>
                    every thing: shoes with shoes, coats with cots, etc. Not knowing anything about what was going on there, I asked a few boys, but
                    no one gave me a real answer, I just found out that we were not permitted to <term ref="#t658" type="subject">talk</term> to each
                    other, suddenly I recognized someone I knew who used to live in one of the buildings in our courtyard, he was taken away 4 days
                    before I was, so having asked him what this was here and where all the <term ref="#t826" type="subject">men</term> and <term
                        ref="#t825" type="subject">women</term> were, he turned away, and with tears in his eyes, he told me just one word: <q>you
                        don’t have any mother or sister any more</q>. Before he managed to tell me what happened to them and how, 2 <term ref="#t1159"
                        type="subject">Germans</term> ran up to us and started to thrash us in the head with <term ref="#t564" type="subject"
                        >whips</term>, then an additional 25 blows on our bare <term ref="#t555" type="subject">bodies</term>. I got up from the
                    ground with great difficulty, after we <term ref="#t411" type="subject">sorted</term> things for another 2 hours until 10 o'clock
                    in the evening, they herded us to the <term ref="#t837" type="subject">barracks</term>, suddenly they started shouting in German:
                    they <term ref="#t180" type="subject">stabbed</term>
                    <persName ref="#ehri_et_bialas_max" type="ehri">Maks</persName>
                    <note type="gloss">SS‑Unterscharführer Max Bialas was killed on September 10 or 11, 1942 by Meir Berliner, a prisoner. As
                        retaliation, the Germans killed 160 prisoners.</note> with a knife, who then was dying for a couple of hours, then they
                    started to <term ref="#t653" type="subject">shoot</term> at us and <term ref="#t562" type="subject">torture</term> us mercilessly,
                    with whatever they could. We pushed against each other like sheep, and when I fell to the ground, I was <term ref="#t562"
                        type="subject">hit</term>on the fingers with a bayonet. After an hour of being chased like that, they <term ref="#t540"
                        type="subject">killed</term> 100 boys, including the hero [who had stabbed <persName ref="#ehri_et_bialas_max" type="ehri"
                        >Max</persName>], and chased us to the <term ref="#t837" type="subject">barracks</term>, and it was only in the <term
                        ref="#t837" type="subject">barracks</term> that I managed to rip a piece of my <term ref="#t836" type="subject">shirt</term>
                    off to bandage my hand, each one of us laid down on the ground, crying and in <term ref="#t791" type="subject">pain</term>, to
                    rest a little. The boys who had already been there for a few days or weeks already knew that we had to <term ref="#t486"
                        type="subject">get up</term> when the light was still grayish outside and wait until they open the <term ref="#t837"
                        type="subject">barracks</term>, but this time they didn’t open the <term ref="#t837" type="subject">barracks</term>, they only
                        <term ref="#t662" type="subject">threatened</term> us with machine guns and said that they would all kill us in a minute, so
                    waiting impatiently for <term ref="#t829" type="subject">death</term>. They opened the <term ref="#t837" type="subject"
                        >barracks</term> only at 11 o'clock in the morning, shouting <q><foreign xml:lang="de">alles raus</foreign></q>, they put us
                    in rows and took 200 <term ref="#t411" type="subject">boys</term> away, <term ref="#t533" type="subject">shot</term> them with a
                    machine gun and herded the rest to <term ref="#t943" type="subject">work</term>, <term ref="#t653" type="subject">punishing</term>
                    them for 3 days by giving them no <term ref="#t832" type="subject">food</term> or water. In the afternoon, a <term ref="#t1159"
                        type="subject">German</term> came to the group that was <term ref="#t411" type="subject">sorting</term> shoes and took 50 boys
                    away including me, telling us that we were only going to do some light <term ref="#t943" type="subject">work</term> for 10
                    minutes, and took us through the whole yard to some gate, and when we went through that gate my blood froze, I saw a heap of dead
                        <term ref="#t540" type="subject">people</term> lying on the ground, and bloodied boys going up to them with stretchers,
                    grabbing <term ref="#t515" type="subject">corpses</term> by the hands and legs, they laid them on the stretcher and ran away with
                    them, thinking about all of this, I looked on with tears in my eyes, and all of a sudden I felt a blow to my head with a riding
                    crop, the boys who were already there for a few days told us that two boys should take a stretcher and <term ref="#t557"
                        type="subject">carry</term>
                    <term ref="#t515" type="subject">corpses</term> to the pit, I went quickly to the stretcher, and taking the stretcher back, we
                    went in the direction of the <term ref="#t499" type="subject">gas chambers</term>, on the way <pb facs="EHRI-ET-ZIH3010481_02.jpg"
                        n="2"/> to the <term ref="#t499" type="subject">gas chambers</term> they hit us with <term ref="#t564" type="subject"
                        >whips</term>, shouting: <q>faster, you dogs</q>. I ran to the ramp quickly, we put the stretcher on the ground and clumsily
                    laid the <term ref="#t515" type="subject">corpse</term> onto the stretcher, at this moment the <term ref="#t1159" type="subject"
                        >Germans</term> began to <term ref="#t562" type="subject">torture</term> us mercilessly, they threw me to the ground and
                    kicked me in the head, shouting that I hadn’t picked up the<term ref="#t515" type="subject">corpse</term> the right way, that we
                    were supposed to pick them up by the hands and feet and lay them down evenly on the stretcher. I got up off the ground with
                    difficulty and taking the stretcher with my friend, we ran in the direction of the <term ref="#t539" type="subject">pit</term>, on
                    the way to the <term ref="#t539" type="subject">pit</term> boys were running with <term ref="#t515" type="subject">corpses</term>,
                    on after another, and coming closer to the<term ref="#t539" type="subject">pit</term> I saw another tragic scene, in the <term
                        ref="#t539" type="subject">pit</term> I saw only a huge puddle of blood and when the <term ref="#t515" type="subject"
                        >corpses</term> were thrown into the <term ref="#t539" type="subject">pit</term>, they sunk into the blood, I carried <term
                        ref="#t515" type="subject">corpses</term> for a whole month, then they moved me to the ramp, that <term ref="#t558"
                        type="subject">work</term> was very hard, pulling out <term ref="#t499" type="subject">gassed</term>
                    <term ref="#t515" type="subject">corpses</term>. I pulled out <term ref="#t515" type="subject">corpses</term> for 5 months, all of
                    those <term ref="#t515" type="subject">corpses</term> were thrown into <term ref="#t539" type="subject">pits</term> and spread
                    with chlorine, in <date when="1943-02">1943, in February</date>, the order was issued to dig out all those <term ref="#t515"
                        type="subject">corpses</term> and <term ref="#t516" type="subject">burn</term> them, so 3 <term ref="#t557" type="subject"
                        >diggers</term> were brought in that lowered their buckets into the <term ref="#t539" type="subject">pit</term> and grabbed
                    the pieces of flesh and bones with their teeth and then threw them onto the ground above, boys standing nearby with pitchforks put
                    the pieces of flesh and bones on stretchers and took them to the fire, <term ref="#t516" type="subject">burning</term> 8 thousand
                    people a day.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
