<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://gitlab.inria.fr/dh-projects/workflow-ehri/-/raw/main/ODD/out/ODD-EHRI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="EHRI-BF-19380805_EN" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title xml:lang="de">The Burgenland Jews on the Danube tug-boat. An eyewitness report</title>
				<title xml:lang="en">The Burgenland Jews on the Danube tug boat. An eyewitness report</title>
				<principal><affiliation><orgName>European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</orgName></affiliation></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded by</resp>
					<persName>Michal Frankl</persName>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded by</resp>
					<persName>Wolfgang Schellenbacher</persName>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Funded by</resp>
					<name>Zukunftsfonds der Republik Österreich</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>
					<ref target="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</ref>
				</authority>
				<availability>
					<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title ref="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">BeGrenzte Flucht. Die österreichischen Flüchtlinge an der Grenze zur Tschechoslowakei im
					Krisenjahr 1938</title>
			</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<country ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/countries/gb">Vereinigtes Königreich</country>
						<repository ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/institutions/gb-003348">The Wiener Library for the Study of the Holocaust and
							Genocide</repository>
						<collection>Jewish Central Information Office</collection>
					</msIdentifier>
					<physDesc/>
				</msDesc>
				<bibl>The Wiener Library for the Study of the Holocaust and Genocide, Jewish Central Information Office. <textLang mainLang="en"
						>Original auf Englisch.</textLang></bibl>


			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation>
				<date when="1938-08-05">5. August 1938</date>
				<placeName>Amsterdam</placeName>
				<persName>Schmolka, Marie</persName>
				<orgName>Jewish Central Information Office</orgName>
				<idno>EHRI-BF-19380805</idno>
			</creation>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Hilfsorganisationen</term>
				</keywords>
				<catRef target="Hilfsorganisationen und Interventionen"/>
				<catRef target="Vertreibungspolitik"/>
				<catRef target="Flüchtlingspolitik"/>
				<catRef target="Fluchtberichte"/>
			</textClass>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">Englisch</language>
			</langUsage>
			<abstract>
				<p/>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="transcription">
				<pb facs="EHRI-BF-19380805_01.jpg" n="1"/>
				<!-- <p>When ordering please quote<placeName ref="#amsterdam"
          >Amsterdam</placeName>, Z. V 38 / 57 Jan van Eijck Straat 14</p> -->
				<!--<p><date when="1938-08-05">August 5, 1938</date></p>-->
				<p>Dear Sir –</p>
				<p>The revolting fate of 68 <placeName ref="#burgenland">BURGENLAND</placeName>
					<term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term>, driven from their home, received into no neighbouring country, nor allowed to
					return, has been commented upon troughout the international Press.</p>
				<p>Now we receive the report, which we enclose, of distress still encompassing the persecuted, our authority being <persName
						ref="#ehri_bf_schmolka_marie">Mrs. M. SCHMOLKA</persName>, director of the <orgName ref="#g395">Hicem</orgName>
					<placeName ref="#prague">Prague</placeName>.</p>
				<p>You are free to make such use of the report as you think fit. <persName ref="#ehri_bf_schmolka_marie">Mrs. SCHMOLKA</persName>,
					however, does not wish her name to be mentioned, nor, as usual, must we be named as your source.</p>
				<p rend="margin noindent">Yours faithfully,</p>
				<p rend="margin"><orgName ref="#ehri_bf_jewish_central_information_office">JEWISH CENTRAL INFORMATION OFFICE</orgName></p>
				<p rend="margin"><orgName ref="#ehri_bf_public_service_institute">Public Service Institute</orgName></p>
				<p/>
				<pb facs="EHRI-BF-19380805_02.jpg" n="2"/>
				<p rend="center">THE <placeName ref="#burgenland">BURGENLAND</placeName>
					<term ref="#t864" type="subject">JEWS</term> on the <hi rend="u">DANUBE TUG – BOAT</hi>
				</p>
				<p rend="center">
					<hi rend="u">An Eye Witness Report</hi>
				</p>
				<p>On <date when="1938-04-16">April 16, 1938</date>, the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jewish inhabitants</term> of <placeName
						ref="#kittsee">Kittsee</placeName> and <placeName ref="#pama">Pama, Burgenland, Austria</placeName>, were ejected from their
					homes, robbed of what money and identity papers they had and, during the night, marooned on some small island in the <placeName
						ref="#czechoslovakia">Czech</placeName> section of the <placeName ref="#danube-river">Danube</placeName>. On <date
						when="1938-04-17">April 17</date>, they were found by the <placeName ref="#czechoslovakia">Czech</placeName> frontier guard
					and taken to <placeName ref="#bratislava">Bratislava</placeName>. That very same day they were expelled from <placeName
						ref="#czechoslovakia">Czecho-Slovakia</placeName> and once again taken to the <placeName ref="#federal-republic-of-germany"
						>German</placeName> border. On a narrow streak, “No-man’s-land”, somewhere between the borders of <placeName
						ref="#czechoslovakia">Czecho-Slovakia</placeName>, <placeName ref="#hungary">Hungaria</placeName> and <placeName
						ref="#republic-of-austria">Austria</placeName>, they spent three days and nights, in the bitter cold, half starved, and
					without a roof over their heads, between the fixed bayonets of the sentries of all 3 countries which they were not allowed to
					enter. Some of them, 17 in all, managed to get back to <placeName ref="#kittsee">Kittsee</placeName>, where the old men and
					children were locked up in a cellar, and the grown ups, men and women, were made do hard <term ref="#t555" type="subject"
						>scrubbing work</term>. Exhausted from 3 days’ starving, the poor people’s strength threatened to fail, but ruthless beating
					put them to <term ref="#t556" type="subject">work</term> again. During the night, after a 30 miles walk, they were taken back to
					the <placeName ref="#czechoslovakia">Czech</placeName> frontier.</p>
				<p>At long last the <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jews</term> of <placeName ref="#bratislava">Bratislava</placeName> found a
					temporary way-out. They hired a tug-boat, which landed on the <placeName ref="#hungary">Hungarian</placeName> side of the
						<placeName ref="#danube-river">Danube</placeName>, near <placeName ref="#rajka">Royka</placeName>, and received the people, 68
					altogether, agricultural workers and merchants, infants and 80 years old men. No country along the <placeName ref="#danube-river"
						>Danube</placeName> being prepared to grant the <term ref="#t101" type="subject">refugees</term> leave on land, the <placeName
						ref="#hungary">Hungarian</placeName> authorities extend the permit from week to week, hoping that the <term ref="#t868"
						type="subject">Jewish organisations</term> will secure their <term ref="#t203" type="subject">emigration</term> overseas. It
					is now three months that these people, smitten with despair, refused by every country, and even grudged the stay aboard the ship –
					it is now three months that they are thus kept in the vague hope of salvation.</p>
				<p><pb facs="EHRI-BF-19380805_03.jpg" n="3"/>Efforts were made to induce various countries overseas to receive these unfortunates.
					Though some of the inmates of the boat managed to <term ref="#t203" type="subject">emigrate</term> to the <placeName
						ref="#united-states">United States</placeName>, the majority could not be <term ref="#t203" type="subject">emigrated</term>,
					being unable to comply with the requirements set up by the countries overseas. It was in full realisation of this plight of theirs
					that we went to see the <term ref="#t101" type="subject">refugees</term> on the boat, on July 10.</p>
				<p>We have seen their unspeakable mental distress, even increased by physical torture, as they either must stay in the narrow rooms
					downstairs which are infested with rats and vermin, or on the upper deck where they are left to the weather’s mood.</p>
				<p>There must be an end to this awful tragedy. It is not enough that <term ref="#t864" type="subject">Jewry</term> must suffer all the
					humiliation that is being heaped upon it? Are we going to proclaim no, before the whole world, our utter helplessness, deliver up
					these poorest of the poor to the <orgName ref="#g350">Gestapo</orgName>, and allow a mass <term ref="#t217" type="subject"
						>suicide</term>? We have taken down all particulars of every one of these unfortunates, and in addition, worked out a plan to
					lead this problem towards its solution, it being in the last resort nothing more than a question of finance: 4.000 Pounds.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
