<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/EHRI/ehri-online-editions/main/ODD/out/ODD_EHRI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="EHRI-BF-UH-19380805_EN_CS">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title xml:lang="de">The Burgenland Jews on the Danube tug-boat. An eyewitness report</title>
				<title xml:lang="cs">Burgenlandští Židé na vlečném člunu na Dunaji. Zpráva očitého svědka</title>
				<title xml:lang="en">The Burgenland Jews on the Danube tug boat. An eyewitness report</title>
				<principal><affiliation><orgName>European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</orgName></affiliation></principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Edited by</resp>
					<orgName>BeGrenzte Flucht. Die österreichischen Flüchtlinge an der Grenze zur Tschechoslowakei im Krisenjahr 1938</orgName>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Edited by</resp>
					<persName>Michal Frankl</persName>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Edited by</resp>
					<persName>Wolfgang Schellenbacher</persName>
				</respStmt>
				<funder>Zukunftsfonds der Republik Österreich</funder>
				<funder>Grantová agentura ČR</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority>
					<ref target="https://www.ehri-project.eu/">European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</ref>
				</authority>
				<availability>
					<licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Attribution 4.0 International</licence>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title>Begrentze Flucht</title>
			</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<msDesc>
					<msIdentifier>
						<institution><orgName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/institutions/gb-003348">The Wiener Library for the Study of the Holocaust and Genocide</orgName><address>
								<street>29 Russell Square</street>
								<postCode>WC1B 5DP</postCode>
								<settlement>London</settlement>
								<country ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/countries/gb">United Kingdom</country>
							</address></institution>
						<collection>Jewish Central Information Office</collection>
					</msIdentifier>
					<physDesc/>
				</msDesc>
				<bibl>The Wiener Library for the Study of the Holocaust and Genocide, Jewish Central Information Office. <textLang mainLang="en">Original auf Englisch.</textLang></bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p xml:lang="fr">L'encodage de ce document s'est fait dans le cadre du travail sur les éditions en ligne EHRI</p>
				<p xml:lang="en">The encoding of this document is part of the work on the EHRI Online Editions</p>
				<p xml:lang="de">Die Kodierung dieses Dokuments ist Teil der Arbeit an den EHRI Online Editions</p>
			</projectDesc>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation>
				<origDate when="1938-08-05">5. August 1938</origDate>
				<origPlace>Amsterdam</origPlace>
				<persName>Schmolka, Marie</persName>
				<orgName>Jewish Central Information Office</orgName>
			</creation>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Hilfsorganisationen</term>
				</keywords>
				<catRef target="Hilfsorganisationen und Interventionen"/>
				<catRef target="Vertreibungspolitik"/>
				<catRef target="Flüchtlingspolitik"/>
				<catRef target="Fluchtberichte"/>
			</textClass>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">Englisch</language>
			</langUsage>
			<abstract>
				<p/>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when-iso="2024-05-27" who="#floriane.chiffoleau">Upgrading TEI encoding</change>
			<change when-iso="2018" who="#ehri">Encoding of the file</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="transcription">
				<div type="original" xml:lang="en">
					<pb facs="EHRI-BF-19380805_01.jpg" n="1"/>
					<!-- <p>When ordering please quote<placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2759794/amsterdam.html"
          >Amsterdam</placeName>, Z. V 38 / 57 Jan van Eijck Straat 14</p> -->
					<!--<p><date when="1938-08-05">August 5, 1938</date></p>-->
					<p>Dear Sir –</p>
					<p>The revolting fate of 68 <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2781194/burgenland.html">BURGENLAND</placeName>
						<term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-864" type="subject">Jews</term>, driven from their home, received into no neighbouring country, nor allowed to return, has been commented upon troughout the international Press.</p>
					<p>Now we receive the report, which we enclose, of distress still encompassing the persecuted, our authority being <persName ref="#ehri_bf_schmolka_marie">Mrs. M. SCHMOLKA</persName>, director of the <orgName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_cb-395">Hicem</orgName>
						<placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/3067696/prague.html">Prague</placeName>.</p>
					<p>You are free to make such use of the report as you think fit. <persName ref="#ehri_bf_schmolka_marie">Mrs. SCHMOLKA</persName>, however, does not wish her name to be mentioned, nor, as usual, must we be named as your source.</p>
					<p rend="margin noindent">Yours faithfully,</p>
					<p rend="margin"><orgName ref="#ehri_bf_jewish_central_information_office">JEWISH CENTRAL INFORMATION OFFICE</orgName></p>
					<p rend="margin"><orgName ref="#ehri_bf_public_service_institute">Public Service Institute</orgName></p>
					<p/>
					<pb facs="EHRI-BF-19380805_02.jpg" n="2"/>
					<p rend="center">THE <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2781194/burgenland.html">BURGENLAND</placeName>
						<term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-864" type="subject">JEWS</term> on the <hi rend="u">DANUBE TUG – BOAT</hi>
					</p>
					<p rend="center">
						<hi rend="u">An Eye Witness Report</hi>
					</p>
					<p>On <date when="1938-04-16">April 16, 1938</date>, the <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-864" type="subject">Jewish inhabitants</term> of <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2774348/kittsee.html">Kittsee</placeName> and <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2769259/pama.html">Pama, Burgenland, Austria</placeName>, were ejected from their homes, robbed of what money and identity papers they had and, during the night, marooned on some small island in the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/8505031/czechoslovakia.html">Czech</placeName> section of the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/791630/danube-river.html">Danube</placeName>. On <date when="1938-04-17">April 17</date>, they were found by the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/8505031/czechoslovakia.html">Czech</placeName> frontier guard and taken to <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/3060972/bratislava.html">Bratislava</placeName>. That very same day they were expelled from <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/8505031/czechoslovakia.html">Czecho-Slovakia</placeName> and once again taken to the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2921044/federal-republic-of-germany.html">German</placeName> border. On a narrow streak, “No-man’s-land”, somewhere
						between the borders of <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/8505031/czechoslovakia.html">Czecho-Slovakia</placeName>, <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/719819/hungary.html">Hungaria</placeName> and <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2782113/republic-of-austria.html">Austria</placeName>, they spent three days and nights, in the bitter cold, half starved, and without a roof over their heads, between the fixed bayonets of the sentries of all 3 countries which they were not
						allowed to enter. Some of them, 17 in all, managed to get back to <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2774348/kittsee.html">Kittsee</placeName>, where the old men and children were locked up in a cellar, and the grown ups, men and women, were made do hard <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-555" type="subject">scrubbing work</term>. Exhausted from 3 days’ starving, the poor people’s strength threatened to fail, but ruthless beating put them to <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-556" type="subject">work</term> again. During the night, after a 30 miles walk, they were taken back to the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/8505031/czechoslovakia.html">Czech</placeName> frontier.</p>
					<p>At long last the <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-864" type="subject">Jews</term> of <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/3060972/bratislava.html">Bratislava</placeName> found a temporary way-out. They hired a tug-boat, which landed on the
							<placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/719819/hungary.html">Hungarian</placeName> side of the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/791630/danube-river.html">Danube</placeName>, near <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/3045991/rajka.html">Royka</placeName>, and
						received the people, 68 altogether, agricultural workers and merchants, infants and 80 years old men. No country along the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/791630/danube-river.html">Danube</placeName> being prepared to grant the <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-101" type="subject">refugees</term> leave on land, the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/719819/hungary.html">Hungarian</placeName> authorities extend the permit from week to week, hoping that the <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-868" type="subject">Jewish organisations</term> will secure their <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-203" type="subject">emigration</term> overseas. It is now three months that these
						people, smitten with despair, refused by every country, and even grudged the stay aboard the ship – it is now three months that they are thus kept in the vague hope of salvation.</p>
					<p><pb facs="EHRI-BF-19380805_03.jpg" n="3"/>Efforts were made to induce various countries overseas to receive these unfortunates. Though some of the inmates of the boat managed to <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-203" type="subject">emigrate</term>
						to the <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/6252001/united-states.html">United States</placeName>, the majority could not be <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-203" type="subject">emigrated</term>, being unable to comply with the requirements set
						up by the countries overseas. It was in full realisation of this plight of theirs that we went to see the <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-101" type="subject">refugees</term> on the boat, on July 10.</p>
					<p>We have seen their unspeakable mental distress, even increased by physical torture, as they either must stay in the narrow rooms downstairs which are infested with rats and vermin, or on the upper deck where they are left to the weather’s mood.</p>
					<p>There must be an end to this awful tragedy. It is not enough that <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-864" type="subject">Jewry</term> must suffer all the humiliation that is being heaped upon it? Are we going to proclaim no, before the whole world,
						our utter helplessness, deliver up these poorest of the poor to the <orgName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_cb-350">Gestapo</orgName>, and allow a mass <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-217" type="subject">suicide</term>? We
						have taken down all particulars of every one of these unfortunates, and in addition, worked out a plan to lead this problem towards its solution, it being in the last resort nothing more than a question of finance: 4.000 Pounds.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="translation" xml:lang="cs">
					<pb facs="EHRI-UH-19380805_01.jpg" n="1"/>
					<!-- <p>When ordering please quote<placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2759794/amsterdam.html"
          >Amsterdam</placeName>, Z. V 38 / 57 Jan van Eijck Straat 14</p> -->
					<!--<p><date when="1938-08-05">August 5, 1938</date></p>-->
					<p>Vážený pane –</p>
					<p>Otřesný osud šedesáti osmi <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2781194/burgenland.html">BURGENLANDSKÝCH</placeName>
						<term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-864" type="subject">Židů</term>, vyhnaných ze svých domovů, odmítnutých všemi sousedním státy, bez možnosti návratu, se stal centrem pozornosti mezinárodního tisku.</p>
					<p>Nyní jsme obdrželi přiloženou zprávu o strádání, které stále stíhá pronásledované, opírající se o svědectví Paní <persName ref="#ehri_bf_schmolka_marie">M. SCHMOLKOVÉ</persName>, ředitelky <orgName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_cb-395">Hicem</orgName> v
							<placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/3067696/prague.html">Praze</placeName>.</p>
					<p>Zprávu můžete využít, jakkoli uznáte za vhodné. Je ale přání paní <persName ref="#ehri_bf_schmolka_marie">SCHMOLKOVÉ</persName>, aby nikde nebylo zmíněno její jméno, a rovněž – jako vždy – nesmí být jako zdroj informací uvedena naše organizace.</p>
					<p>V úctě,</p>
					<p>
						<ref target="#ehri_bf_jewish_central_information_offic">Ústřední židovská informační kancelář</ref>
					</p>
					<p>
						<ref target="#ehri_bf_public_service_institute">Institut služeb veřejnosti</ref>
					</p>
					<p>
						<placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2781194/burgenland.html"/>
					</p>
					<p><placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2781194/burgenland.html">BURGENLANDŠTÍ</placeName>
						<term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-864" type="subject">ŽIDÉ</term> NA VLEČNÉM ČLUNU NA DUNAJI</p>
					<p>Zpráva očitého svědka</p>
					<p>16. dubna 1938 byli <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-864" type="subject">židovští obyvatelé</term>
						<placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2774348/kittsee.html">Kittsee</placeName> a <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2769259/pama.html">Pamy, Burgenland, Rakousko</placeName> vyhnáni ze svých domovů, obráni o veškeré prostředky i osobní dokumenty a v noci pak ponecháni
						svému osudu na malém ostrově v <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/8505031/czechoslovakia.html">československé</placeName> části řeky <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/791630/danube-river.html">Dunaj</placeName>. 17. dubna je nalezli příslušníci <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/8505031/czechoslovakia.html">československé</placeName> pohraniční stráže a odvedli je do <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/3060972/bratislava.html">Bratislavy</placeName>. V ten samý den byli vyhoštěni z <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/8505031/czechoslovakia.html">Československa</placeName> a znovu odvedeni k <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2921044/federal-republic-of-germany.html">německým</placeName> hranicím. Na úzkém proužku <q>země nikoho</q> někde mezi
						hranicemi <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/8505031/czechoslovakia.html">Československa</placeName>, <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/719819/hungary.html">Maďarska</placeName> a <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2782113/republic-of-austria.html">Rakouska</placeName> strávili tři dny a noci na třeskutém mrazu, bez střechy nad hlavou a hladoví, majíce na sebe přitom namířené bodáky vojáků všech tří zemí, do kterých nesměli vstoupit. Někteří z nich, celkem 17, se dokázali vrátit do <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2774348/kittsee.html">Kittsee</placeName>, kde byli starci a děti uzamčeni ve sklepě a dospělí, muži i ženy, byli nuceni těžce pracovat - <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-555" type="subject">drhnout</term> podlahy.
						Po třídenním hladovění byli na konci svých sil, ale nemilosrdné bití jim nedovolilo v <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-556" type="subject">práci</term> polevit. V noci, po pochodu 30 mil dlouhém, byli navráceni k hranicím s <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/8505031/czechoslovakia.html">Československem</placeName>.</p>
					<p>Po nekonečném čekání se podařilo <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-864" type="subject">Židům</term> z <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/3060972/bratislava.html">Bratislavy</placeName> přijít s dočasným řešením. Pronajali si vlečný člun, který
						přistál na <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/719819/hungary.html">maďarské</placeName> straně <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/791630/danube-river.html">Dunaje</placeName>, poblíž <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/3045991/rajka.html">Rajky</placeName>, a na
						který se nalodilo celkem 68 osob – zemědělců, kupců, malých dětí i osmdesátiletých starců. Žádná ze zemí na březích <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/791630/danube-river.html">Dunaje</placeName> však nebyla ochotna povolit člunu přistát a povolit <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-101" type="subject">uprchlíkům</term> vstoupit na pevninu. <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/719819/hungary.html">Maďarské</placeName> orgány prodlužovaly lodi povolení pobytu ve svých výsostných vodách co
						týden, přičemž doufaly, že <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-868" type="subject"> židovské organizace</term> nakonec zajistí jejich <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-203" type="subject">emigraci</term> do zámoří. Nyní
						jsou tomu již tři měsíce, po které jsou tito zoufalí lidé, zavržení všemi státy a čelící nevraživosti, se kterou je vnímána jen jejich samotná přítomnost na palubě, nuceni strádat. Jsou tomu tři měsíce, během nichž vzhlíží k nejisté naději záchrany.</p>
					<p>Bylo vyvinuto nemalé úsilí přesvědčit různé zámořské státy, aby tyto nešťastníky přijaly. I když se některým na člunu uvězněným osobám podařilo <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-203" type="subject">emigrovat</term> do <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/6252001/united-states.html">USA</placeName>, většina možnost <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-203" type="subject">emigrace</term> neměla, protože nebyla schopna vyhovět imigračním požadavkůmstanoveným těmito státy.
						Naše návštěva na lodi 10. července proběhla při plném vědomí jejich vážné situace.</p>
					<p>Byli jsme svědky jejich nevýslovného duševního strádání, násobeného tělesnými útrapami, které jsou způsobeny jak jejich nuceným pobytem v těsných, krysami a havětí zamořených prostorách v podpalubí, tak na palubě, kde jsou vydáni napospas rozmarům počasí.</p>
					<p>Je nezbytné, aby byla tato tragická situace vyřešena. Copak nestačí, že <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-864" type="subject">Židé</term> musí strpět toto ponižování ze všech stran? Copak můžeme před očima celého světa prohlásit, že jsme zcela
						bezmocní, předhodíme ty nejubožejší z ubohých <orgName ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/authorities/ehri_cb-350">Gestapu</orgName> a pro ostatní bude řešením jen hromadná <term ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/keywords/ehri_terms-217" type="subject">sebevražda</term>?
						Pořídili jsme seznam osobních údajů všech těch nešťastníků, a navíc vypracovali plán, který povede k vyřešení problému. Jeho úspěch závisí pouze na finančních prostředcích: 4.000 liber.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>