<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?teipublisher template="document.html"?>
<?xml-model href="../../Guidelines/out/Documentation-Correspondance.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="EHRI-ET-ZIH3010002_EN" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en">Dwojra Szczuczyńska, the „Hotel Polski” affair in Warsaw</title>
                <title xml:lang="fr">Dwojra Szczuczyńska, l'affaire „Hotel Polski” à Varsovie</title>
                <principal><affiliation><orgName>European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</orgName></affiliation></principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <orgName>EHRI Edition of Early Holocaust Testimony</orgName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <persName>Michał Czajka</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <persName>Marta Wojas</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <persName>Dagmara Chełstowska</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <ref target="https://www.ehri-project.eu">European Holocaust Research Infrastructure</ref>
                </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0">Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title type="main">EHRI Edition of Early Holocaust Testimonies</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <location>
                            <address>
                                <street>Tłomackie 3/5</street>
                                <postCode>00-090 </postCode>
                                <settlement>Warsaw</settlement>
                                <country ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/countries/pl">Poland</country>
                            </address>
                        </location>
                        <repository ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/institutions/pl-003146">Jewish Historical Institute in Warsaw</repository>
                        <collection ref="https://portal.ehri-project.eu/units/pl-003146-301#desc-pol">Holocaust Survivor Testimonies (coll.
                            301)</collection>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <physDesc/>
                </msDesc>
                <bibl>Jewish Historical Institute in Warsaw, Holocaust Survivor Testimonies (coll. 301), Dwojra Szczucińska Testimony (301/2).
                        <textLang mainLang="pl">Original in Polish.</textLang></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="fr">L'encodage de ce document s'est fait dans le cadre du projet 'EHRI Edition of Early Holocaust Testimonies'</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The encoding of this document is part of the project 'EHRI Edition of Early Holocaust Testimonies'</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation><date when="1944-09-04">4. 9. 1944</date>, <persName ref="#ehri_et_szczucinska_dwojra">Dwojra Szczucińska</persName>, <persName
                    ref="#ehri_et_asz_marek">Marek Asz</persName>, <placeName ref="#warsaw">Warsaw</placeName>, <term ref="#t1146" type="subject"
                    >visas</term>, <term ref="#t496" type="subject">concentration camps</term>
                <idno>EHRI-ET-ZIH3010002</idno></creation>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>testimony</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">Polish</language>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <abstract>
                <p>Testimony of Dwojra Szczuczyńska on the “Hotel Polski affair”, a Gestapo trap resulting in the death of about 3000 Jews who left
                    their hiding places on the “Aryan side”, with specific reference to the role of Lolek Skosowski, a Gestapo agent.</p>
            </abstract>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when-iso="2022-07-21" who="#floriane.chiffoleau">Added the original version of the testimony</change>
            <change when-iso="2021-11-05" who="#floriane.chiffoleau">Upgrading TEI encoding</change>
            <change when-iso="2021-10-29" who="#floriane.chiffoleau">Upgrading TEI encoding</change>
            <change when-iso="2020" who="#ehri">Encoding of the file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="original">
                <p>Archiwum Żydowskiego Instytutu Historycznego w Warszawie</p>
                <p>Relacje z Zagłady (zespół 301)</p>
                <p>Relacja <persName ref="#ehri_et_szczucinska_dwojra" type="ehri">Dwojry Szczuczyńskiej</persName> (sygn. 301/2) </p>
                <p>Oryginał, rękopis, 2 strony, 210 x 295 mm, język polski</p>
                <pb facs="EHRI-ET-ZIH3010002_01.jpg" n="1"/>
                <p>Pani <persName ref="#ehri_et_szczucinska_dwojra" type="ehri">Szczuczyńska Dwojra</persName> zamieszkała w <placeName ref="#warsaw"
                        type="ehri">Warszawie</placeName> opowiada o tak zwanym <q>Hotelu</q> dla Żydów urządzonego przez <term ref="#t1159"
                        type="subject">Niemców</term> przy współudziale <orgName ref="#g350" type="ehri">gestapowców</orgName> żydowskich.</p>
                <p>Było to w <date when="1943-05">maju 1943</date> roku rozeszła się wiadomość, że Żydzi <term ref="#t1149" type="subject">obywatele
                        zagraniczni</term>, mają możność wyjazdu za granicę. Była to pułapka na Żydów, urządzonych bądź to <term ref="#t262"
                        type="subject">ukrytych</term> po stronie <term ref="#t373" type="subject">aryjskiej</term>. Były (rzekomo) na <orgName
                        ref="#g350" type="ehri">Gestapo</orgName> certyfikaty dla Żydów, którzy <term ref="#t745" type="subject">zginęli</term> w
                    akcji, <term ref="#t1159" type="subject">Niemcy</term> idąc na rękę Żydom ocalałym, sprzedawali <term ref="#t1149" type="subject"
                        >obywatelstwa</term> i w ten sposób podstępem zgarniali naiwnych.<note type="gloss">Istniały dwa rodzaje dokumentów mających
                        rzekomo zapewnić ich posiadaczom bezpieczeństwo: certyfikaty, wystawione przez władze brytyjskie, uprawniające do wjazdu do
                        Palestyny oraz paszporty państw Ameryki Łacińskiej.</note> Na czele tej afery, stał <orgName ref="#g350" type="ehri"
                        >gestapowiec</orgName> Żyd <persName ref="#ehri_et_skosowski_lolek" type="ehri">Lolek Skosowski</persName> mieszkaniec
                        <placeName ref="#lodz" type="ehri">Łodzi</placeName>(do ostatniej chwili zamieszkały we <placeName ref="#lviv" type="ehri"
                        >Lwowie</placeName> przy <placeName ref="#lviv" type="ehri">ulicy Teresy 4</placeName> i został <term ref="#t532"
                        type="subject">zabity</term> przez partię), który dla podkreślenia wiarygodności tej imprezy poświęcił własną <term
                        ref="#t822" type="subject">rodzinę</term>, sprowadzając ją z <placeName ref="#l513" type="ghetto">getta
                    łódzkiego</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Naiwnych werbowano przy ulicy Długiej w Hotelu Polskim. Przed bramą stała wacha <note type="gloss">Wacha (niem.
                            <foreign>Wache</foreign>) – posterunek wartowniczy</note> z bronią, która przestrzegała porządku i rozpędzała gapiów.
                    Ofiarą tego padli Żydzi najbogatsi, którzy płacili po kilkaset tysięcy złotych za certyfikat. Ściągali tam z wytwornym bagażem. Na
                    miejscu była restauracja, fryzjer. Panie i Panowie czuli się jak na wytwornym okręcie. Spośród Żydów wyłonił się Komitet, który
                    zaopiekował <pb facs="EHRI-ET-ZIH3010002_02.jpg" n="2"/> się <term ref="#t327" type="subject">osieroconymi</term>
                    <term ref="#t824" type="subject">dziećmi</term>, które miały rzekomo wyjechać do <placeName ref="#palestine" type="ehri"
                        >Palestyny.</placeName> Dzięki <q>wielkoduszności</q>
                    <orgName ref="#g350" type="ehri">gestapowców</orgName>, zapłacie w <q>naturze</q> i tym podobne przyjmowano biedne <term
                        ref="#t327" type="subject">sieroty</term>. W miarę napływania naiwnych wysyłano <term ref="#t521" type="subject"
                        >transporty</term>. Było takich trzy. Pierwszy do <placeName ref="#vittel" type="ehri">Wittel</placeName>, <note type="gloss"
                        >Wittel – właściwie Vittel, uzdrowisko we Francji. Grupa przetrzymywana w Vittel została następnie wywieziona do obozu zagłady
                        w Auschwitz.</note> skąd przychodziły nawet listy, drugi do <placeName ref="#hannover" type="ehri">Hanoweru</placeName> trzeci
                    i ostatni na <placeName ref="#warsaw" type="ehri">Pawiak</placeName>.<note type="gloss">Dalsze grupy mieszkańców <q>Hotelu
                            Polskiego</q> wywieziono do obozu koncentracyjnego Bergen-Belsen.</note></p>
                <p>Po pewnym czasie przestały nadchodzić wiadomości. Z <placeName ref="#hannover" type="ehri">Hanoweru</placeName> przyszła kartka
                    jednej <term ref="#t825" type="subject">Pani</term> pisana omówionym hasłem do znajomych demaskująca cały ogrom afery, mianowicie
                    zdanie <q>dzieje nam się bardzo dobrze</q> miało oznaczać <term ref="#t529" type="subject">zagładę</term> grupy.</p>
                <p>Ostatni <term ref="#t521" type="subject">transport</term> zajechał niedaleko, bo tylko do <term ref="#t669" type="subject"
                        >więzienia</term> tak zwanego <placeName ref="#warsaw" type="ehri">Pawiaka</placeName>, <term ref="#t532" type="subject"
                        >mordowni</term> setek tysięcy ludzi.</p>
                <p>Afera tak zwanego <q>hotelu</q> wyłowiła z dzielnicy <term ref="#t373" type="subject">aryjskiej</term> około 3000 Żydów. Byli to
                    ludzie, którzy mieli wszelkie dane: wygląd, <term ref="#t831" type="subject">warunki materialne</term> i tak zwane urządzenie
                    czyli <term ref="#t943" type="subject">praca</term> na różnych placówkach (kolej, poczta, straż ogniowa) i mieli możność
                    przetrwania okresu barbarzyństwa <term ref="#t1159" type="subject">niemieckiego</term>.</p>
                <p><note type="gloss">Podpis:</note>
                    <persName ref="#ehri_et_szczucinska_dwojra" type="ehri">Szczuczyńska</persName></p>
                <p><placeName ref="#lublin" type="ehri">Lublin</placeName> dnia <date when="1944-09-04">4.9.1944</date></p>
                <p>Zebrał <persName ref="#ehri_et_asz_marek" type="ehri">M. Asz</persName></p>
            </div>
            <div type="transcription">
                <p>
                    <persName ref="#ehri_et_szczucinska_dwojra" type="ehri">Dwojra Szczuczyńska</persName> Testimony (doc. 301/2)</p>
                <p>Original, manuscript, 2 pages, 210 x 295 mm, Polish language</p>
                <pb facs="EHRI-ET-ZIH3010002_01.jpg" n="1"/>
                <p><persName ref="#ehri_et_szczucinska_dwojra" type="ehri">Dwojra Szczuczyńska</persName>, residing in <placeName ref="#warsaw"
                        type="ehri">Warsaw</placeName>, tells about the <q>Hotel</q> for Jews that was set up by <term ref="#t1159" type="subject"
                        >Germans</term> in cooperation with the Jewish <orgName ref="#g350" type="ehri">Gestapo</orgName> men.</p>
                <p>In <date when="1943-05">May 1943</date>, the news came that Jews who were <term ref="#t1149" type="subject">foreign citizens</term>
                    could leave the country. This was a trap for Jews who were settled or in <term ref="#t262" type="subject">hiding</term> on the
                        <term ref="#t373" type="subject">Aryan</term> side. There were (it was said) certificates at the <orgName ref="#g350"
                        type="ehri">Gestapo</orgName> for Jews who had <term ref="#t745" type="subject">died</term> in action, <term ref="#t1159"
                        type="subject">Germans</term> making it convenient for the Jews who had survived, sold <term ref="#t1149" type="subject"
                        >citizenships</term> and with that underhanded method caught the naïve ones. <note type="gloss">There were two types of
                        documents which were supposed to provide their holders security: certificates issued by British authorities, authorizing entry
                        to Palestine, and the passports of the Latin American countries.</note>At the head of this scam was a Jewish <orgName
                        ref="#g350" type="ehri">Gestapo</orgName> officer named <persName ref="#ehri_et_skosowski_lolek" type="ehri">Lolek
                        Skosowski</persName>, a resident of <placeName ref="#lodz" type="ehri">Łódź</placeName> (who lived until the last minute in
                        <placeName ref="#lviv" type="ehri">Lwów</placeName> at <placeName ref="#lviv" type="ehri">4 Teresy Street</placeName> and was
                        <term ref="#t532" type="subject">killed</term> by the party), who sacrificed his own <term ref="#t822" type="subject"
                        >family</term> to underscore the trustworthiness of this program, having taken them out of the <placeName ref="#l513"
                        type="ghetto">Łódź ghetto</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Naïve people were recruited at the <q>Hotel Polski</q> on Długa Street. At the gate there was an armed <foreign>guard
                        [wacha]</foreign>, <note type="gloss">Wacha (German ‑ Wache) – guard post.</note> who kept order and chased away onlookers.
                    The richest Jews fell victim to this, who would pay several hundred thousand <foreign xml:lang="pl">złotys</foreign> each for a
                    certificate. They came with their fancy baggage. There was a restaurant and barber shop right there. The ladies and gentlemen felt
                    as if they were on a fancy ship. A committee was formed <pb facs="EHRI-ET-ZIH3010002_02.jpg" n="2"/> from among the Jews, which
                    took care of <term ref="#t327" type="subject">orphaned</term>
                    <term ref="#t824" type="subject">children</term> who were allegedly supposed to leave for <placeName ref="#palestine" type="ehri"
                        >Palestine</placeName>. Thanks to the <q>big-heartedness</q> of the <orgName ref="#g350" type="ehri">Gestapo</orgName>, poor
                        <term ref="#t327" type="subject">orphans</term> were accepted in exchange for payments <q>in-kind</q> and similar
                    arrangements. <term ref="#t521" type="subject">Transports</term> were sent depending on how many naïve people were taken in. There
                    were three such <term ref="#t521" type="subject">transports</term>. The first was to <placeName ref="#vittel" type="ehri"
                        >Wittel</placeName>
                    <note type="gloss">Wittel – Vittel, a spa town in France. Group held in Vittel was then deported to the death camp at
                        Auschwitz.</note>, from whence letter were even sent, the second went to <placeName ref="#hannover-landeshauptstadt"
                        type="ehri">Hannover</placeName>, the third and last to <placeName ref="#warsaw" type="ehri">Pawiak</placeName>. <note
                        type="gloss">Further groups of residents of <q>Hotel Polski</q> were deported to the concentration camp at
                        Bergen‑Belsen.</note></p>
                <p>After a while, there ceased to be any news. A card from <placeName ref="#hannover-landeshauptstadt" type="ehri"
                        >Hannover</placeName> came from one <term ref="#t825" type="subject">woman</term>, written in an arranged code to her friends,
                    which unmasked the enormity of the scam, namely the sentence <q>we are doing very well</q> was to mean the group’s <term
                        ref="#t529" type="subject">extermination</term>.</p>
                <p>The last <term ref="#t521" type="subject">transport</term> did not go far, only to the <term ref="#t669" type="subject"
                        >prison</term> known as <placeName ref="#warsaw" type="ehri">Pawiak</placeName>, hundreds of thousands of people were <term
                        ref="#t532" type="subject">killed</term>.</p>
                <p>The <q>hotel</q> scam caught about 3,000 people from the <term ref="#t373" type="subject">Aryan</term> neighborhood. They were
                    people who had every opportunity: they looked good, had <term ref="#t831" type="subject">living conditions</term>, and were <q>set
                        up</q>, which means they had <term ref="#t943" type="subject">work</term> in various places (railroad, post office, fire
                    department) and they had the possibility of surviving the period of <term ref="#t1159" type="subject">German</term> barbarity.</p>
                <p><note type="gloss">[Signature:]</note><persName ref="#ehri_et_szczucinska_dwojra" type="ehri">Szczuczyńska</persName></p>
                <p><placeName ref="#lublin" type="ehri">Lublin</placeName>, <date when="1944-09-04">September 4, 1944</date></p>
                <p>Collected by <persName ref="#ehri_et_asz_marek" type="ehri">M. Asz</persName></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
